<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An adioynder to the late Catholike new yeares gift, or explication of the oath of allegeance Wherein certaine principall difficulties, obiected by a very learned Roman-Catholike, against the sayd New-yeares gift, and explication of the oath, are very clearely explained. Published by E.I. the author of the New-yeares gift.</title>
            <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835979</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 217)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An adioynder to the late Catholike new yeares gift, or explication of the oath of allegeance Wherein certaine principall difficulties, obiected by a very learned Roman-Catholike, against the sayd New-yeares gift, and explication of the oath, are very clearely explained. Published by E.I. the author of the New-yeares gift.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Eliot's Court Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.I. = Thomas Preston.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>P. 54 misnumbered 45.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:217:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:217:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADIOYNDER TO THE LATE CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE NEW YEARES GIFT, Or <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> of ALLEGEANCE.</p>
            <p>Wherein Certaine principall difficulties, obiected by a very learned <hi>Roman-Catholike,</hi> againſt the ſayd <hi>New-yeares Gift,</hi> and <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> are very clearely explained.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by E. I. the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeares Gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>IHS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Occultari poteſt ad tempus veritas, vinci non poteſt.</p>
               <p>Truth may for a time be ſuppreſſed, but it cannot be ouercome.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Auguſtin in Pſal.</hi> 61.</bibl>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. <hi>1620.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:217:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:217:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the New of this yeere, I preſented to your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>(Deare Country-men) A Catholike New-yeeres gift,</hi> or <hi>A brief, &amp; clear Explication of the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> partly vpon occaſion of the <hi>publike acknowledgment,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Greene,</hi> a very learned Diuine, and <hi>Religious Prieſt</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Benedict,</hi> made of his opinion concerning the ſaid Oath, to wit, <hi>that in his owne priuate iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he thought, that there is nothing in the Oath, which may not, according
<pb facs="tcp:217:3"/>to</hi> Roger Widdringtons <hi>Gloſſe, and Explication, bee lawfully taken by Engliſh Catholikes;</hi> and partly to inſtruct and appeaſe more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the conſciences of you, <hi>my Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Brethren,</hi> concerning the ſaid Oath, then you were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by that falſe, and peſtiferous Explication, compiled by <hi>I. E.</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> commonly called, <hi>The Prelate and the Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Now in the laſt end thereof, I am bold to annex, for your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtruction, a little <hi>Addition,</hi> or <hi>Adioynder</hi> to the aforeſayd <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> vpon occaſion of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> which a <hi>Religious Prieſt</hi> hath made to a very learned <hi>Roman-Catholike,</hi> in anſwer to diuers diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, doubts and ſcruples, which he obiected againſt the ſayd <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> or <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Oath.</hi> By which <hi>Reply</hi> you may clearely ſee, that this difficult, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,
<pb facs="tcp:217:3"/>and ſcandalous contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to <hi>depoſe Princes,</hi> and the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegeance,</hi> is now in ſome ſort brought to a finall iſſue, for that all the exceptions, which hitherto haue beene vrged, or with any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of reaſon may bee alledged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aforeſayd <hi>Oath,</hi> are fully ſatisfied by theſe <hi>foure</hi> generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, which partly in the <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi> and partly in this <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder</hi> are made ſo plaine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that no man of learning and conſcience can contradict the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>firſt aſſertion</hi> is, that it is a doctrine <hi>truely probable</hi> (it being approued by <hi>ſo many</hi> learned Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines, and Lawyers, both ancient and moderne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>ſo many</hi> publike <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon <hi>ſo many</hi> pregnant
<pb facs="tcp:217:4"/>proofes, which are taken from the authority of the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> the doctrine of the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> the practice of the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> and diuers other <hi>Theologicall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>) that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any power, or authority, to <hi>depoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Princes,</hi> or to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of their <hi>Crownes and liues,</hi> for any cauſe, crime, end, or good whatſoeuer. And this <hi>aſſertion</hi> is ſo manifeſt, that the moſt learned and <hi>Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cardinall Peron</hi> not onely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>That the Pope doth tolerate in France, thoſe Catholikes, who hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in this point</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">En Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tier Eſtat. pag. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note>, and, <hi>That this controuerſie ought not to hinder the re-vnion of thoſe, who ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be reconciled to the Church</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">In his Reply. ca. 91. p. 633.</note>, but alſo (which is more to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired) he ſeeketh to excuſe <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe<note n="c" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath Sect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. num. 9.</note>, as though he thought it abſurd for any man to conceiue, that ſo learned a man, as
<pb facs="tcp:217:4"/>
               <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> is, ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely teach, that the doctrine for the <hi>Popes power</hi> to diſpoſe of all temporalls, is an vndoubted point of faith, and to which all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes are bound, to adhere vnder paine of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>ſecond aſſertion</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of theſe <hi>three</hi> points. 1. That a meere probable, and imaginary power, to wit, which is onely in the imagination, conceipt, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of learned Catholikes, and is contradicted by others, is no true, reall, lawfull and ſufficient power, or ground, to puniſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or depriue any man of that; which he actually poſſeſſeth, and to which alſo hee hath a probable title. 2. That it is not lawfull for the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other <hi>Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> to diſpoſſeſſe by violence, or force of Armes, any lawfull <hi>Prince</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:217:5"/>of his Dominions, vnder pretence of any probable title, which is grounded vpon an vncertaine ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall authoritie, eſpecially ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (which is moſt certaine) that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath left in his Church a peaceable way to finde out, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide infallibly the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of all ſuch controuerſed and doubtfull titles. 3. That it is moſt certaine, and out of all controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that a lawfull <hi>Prince,</hi> who is in peaceable poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may lawfully defend himſelf, &amp; his Dominions, againſt all ſuch, that ſhall inuade him &amp; his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, vnder pretence of any ſuch probable title, which is grounded vpon ſpirituall authority, and that hee may lawfully put them to death, as Traytours, or enemies to his Crowne and State, that ſhall in hoſtile manner aſſault him and his Dominions, vnder pretence of
<pb facs="tcp:217:5"/>any ſuch vncertaine, and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed right and authority. And theſe <hi>two aſſertions</hi> do make cleare the <hi>Second Branch</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> wherein is acknowledged, <hi>That the Pope hath not any power, or authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to depoſe the King, to abſolue his Subiects from their allegeance, or to authorize any forraine Prince to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade, or annoy him, or his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>third aſſertion</hi> is, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery falſe doctrine, which is either directly and expreſſely repugnant to the Word of God, or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vertually, and by a neceſſarie conſequence deduced from <hi>two premiſes,</hi> whereof the <hi>one</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely contained in the <hi>holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> euidently knowne by the light of nature, is, both in the opinion of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and alſo of moſt <hi>Catholike Diuines,</hi> truely and properly <hi>hereticall,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:217:6"/>that the <hi>Church</hi> hath not any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to make any Catholike ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or hereſie, but onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, when there is made any doubt thereof, and to make it knowne to all Catholikes, which before her declaration was not knowne to all, but onely to ſome, more or leſſe, who ſaw the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the conſequence deduced from both the premiſes. And by this <hi>aſſertion</hi> the veritie of the <hi>Fourth Branch</hi> is made plaine and manifeſt, for that all the ſtiffe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of the Oath, doe ground all their exceptions againſt that <hi>Branch,</hi> vpon the word <hi>[hereticall.]</hi> So that by the aforeſaid <hi>three aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are cleared all the particular <hi>Branches</hi> of the Oath, for that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the verity of the <hi>Second,</hi> and <hi>Fourth Branch,</hi> is wholly groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the verity and Iuſtice of euery particular clauſe, except onely of
<pb facs="tcp:217:6"/>the <hi>Firſt Branch,</hi> wherein <hi>our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King Iames is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be the lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Branch</hi> is ſo cleere and manifeſt, that no Engliſh Catholike euer durſt be ſo impious and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, as to take the leaſt excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The <hi>Fourth aſſertion</hi> is, that it is no diſobedience, or irreuerence againſt the <hi>See Apostelike</hi> for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes not to obey the <hi>Popes</hi> commandement, whenſoeuer they haue doubt, that it is vniuſt,<note place="margin">Sotus de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegendo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto memb. <hi>3.</hi>q; <hi>2.</hi> Vaſques <hi>and others cited by</hi> Wrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringt. <hi>in the diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of</hi> Schul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cken. <hi>his ſlanders, §. 15.</hi>
               </note> and in preiudice of a third perſon, who is in poſſeſſion of his goods, &amp; good name, ſo that they doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propound to his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> the reaſons of their doubt. This <hi>aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is in plaine &amp; expreſſe tearmes ſet downe by that moſt learned and religious <hi>Dominicus Soto,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by <hi>Vaſques</hi> and many other
<pb facs="tcp:217:7"/>Diuines, grounded vpon manifeſt reaſon, and ſufficiently confirmed by the Canon Law it ſelfe, in <hi>Cap. ſi quando, extra, de Reſcriptis,</hi> where <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> the <hi>third</hi> giueth this aduertiſement to the <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> that <hi>he ought either to obey</hi> the ſaid <hi>Popes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which he enioyned him by his <hi>Breues, or elſe by his letters to yeeld a reaſonable cauſe, why he ought not to obey it.</hi> Whereupon <hi>obſerue,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Gloſſe,</hi> expounding that <hi>Canon, that the Superiours comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ought either to be obeyed, or a cauſe to be yeelded, why it is not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> Seeing therefore, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath by diuerſe publike and printed letters ſignified to his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> in moſt humble manner the reaſons, why Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes thinke themſelues bound not to obey his <hi>Breues</hi> forbidding the Oath, as <hi>conteyning in it many things
<pb facs="tcp:217:7"/>flat contrarie to faith and ſaluation,</hi> becauſe they are grounded, by the bad information of <hi>Card. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and his adherents, vpon <hi>two</hi> very falſe ſuppoſitions, <hi>The one,</hi> that the <hi>Popes power</hi> to <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> is denyed in the Oath, which is manifeſtly falſe, <hi>The other,</hi> that his power to <hi>depoſe Princes</hi> is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted point of faith, which is no leſſe vntrue; neither as yet hath he, or other Catholikes receiued from his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> or any other, any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere or ſatisfaction of theſe their doubts, truely they cannot be iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taxed of any diſobedience, or irreuerence againſt his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> for not obeying his <hi>Breues</hi> in the aforeſaid caſe, but contrariwiſe (as in a caſe not much vnlike very well obſerueth and proueth, that holy and learned <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> S. <hi>Robert,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Apud Matth. Paris pag. <hi>843.</hi> in vita Henrici tertij.</note> in anſwere to certain <hi>Breues</hi> of <hi>Pope Innocentius</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:217:8"/>
               <hi>fourth,</hi> which he thought vniuſt) it were diſobedience, irreuerence, and rebellion againſt <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>See Apostolike</hi> to obey any ſuch <hi>Breues,</hi> which are grounded vpon falſe informations, and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and tend to ſo great diſhonor, and iniurie of <hi>his Maiesty,</hi> and the whole kingdome.</p>
            <p n="7">7 So that with farre greater reaſon might be taxed with diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and irreuerence againſt the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> not only the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid holy <hi>Biſhop S. Robert,</hi> for the cauſe alleaged, but alſo that moſt learned and religious <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus Soto,</hi> and other famous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uins, for contradicting the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> concerning their diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in actuall, but not conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate marriage, and for ſaying, <hi>that the Popes erred therein following the doctrine and opinion of the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> as <hi>hauing in it no ſhew or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb facs="tcp:217:8"/>at all of probabilitie,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sotus in <hi>4.</hi> Diſt. <hi>27.</hi> q <hi>31.</hi> ar. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> then <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Widdrington,</hi> and other Engliſh Catholikes, may be iuſtly taxed of any diſobedience, or irreuerence againſt the <hi>See Apostolike</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> which forbid the Oath, as <hi>conteyning in it many things flat contrarie to faith and ſaluation,</hi> and for ſaying, that he erred therein, following the bad information and opinion of <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> &amp; other Ieſuites, which hath in it a farre leſſe ſhew and ſhadow of probabilitie, then hath the doctrine of the <hi>Canonists</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Popes power to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in actuall, but not conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Marriage: for that all the world now ſeeth plainly, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Popes power</hi> to <hi>excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate</hi> is denied in the Oath, nor the doctrine for his <hi>power to depoſe</hi> is an vndoubted point of faith, but a great controuerſie among lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:217:9"/>Catholikes, and which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ought not to hinder the reunion of thoſe, who ſhould deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">See <hi>Card. Peron</hi> aboue <hi>num.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="8">Conſidering therefore, that the aforeſaid <hi>foure</hi> generall poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are now made ſo plaine and manifeſt, that no man of learning and conſcience can with any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of reaſon contradict them, and that by them all the chiefe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which can be obiected either againſt any particular clauſe of the Oath, or againſt the Oath in generall in regard of the Popes <hi>Breues</hi> forbidding the ſame only in generall tearmes, are moſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered, I beſeech and adiure you (my deare <hi>Catholike brethren</hi>) by the loue you beare to <hi>God,</hi> by the dutie you owe to your <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and by the care you ought to haue of your eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that you will not any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:217:9"/>for feare or flatterie, ſeeke to impugne, eſpecially by indirect, ſiniſter, and vncharitable courſes, ſo manifeſt a truth, to the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie and diſhonour of your <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi> to the great ſcandall of your <hi>Religion,</hi> and to the great danger of your temporal and ſpirituall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw. For aſſure your ſelues, that <hi>Truth is great, and will</hi> in the end <hi>preuaile,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">3. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 4</note> and rather then it ſhall be ouercome, <hi>God</hi> almightie, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of all <hi>Truth,</hi> yea and <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe, will raiſe vp <hi>Babes</hi> &amp; <hi>Infants</hi> to defend it, to the confuſion of the greateſt <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the ſame: and into what danger you caſt your ſoules either by coyning new articles of faith, or concurring and conſenting to the coyners thereof, and by ſeeking in that reſpect to make a <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Diſunion</hi> among your Catholike brethren, you may with feare and
<pb facs="tcp:217:10"/>trembling perceiue by this, which the beloued Diſciple of Chriſt S. <hi>Iohn</hi> threatneth in the end of his <hi>Apocalyps, If any man ſhall add to theſe things, God ſhall add vpon him the plagues written in this booke.</hi> For vndoubtedly whoſoeuer ſhall add to the holy Scripture that which is not Scripture, or to Catholike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe that which is not Catholike, or ſhall belieue with Catholike faith that which is not Catholike, or ſhall forge new articles of faith, or conſent to the forgers thereof, eſpecially in things belonging to temporall allegiance, and ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate himſelfe in Eccleſiaſticall communion from thoſe, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict ſuch forgeries, and cauſe a <hi>Schiſme</hi> or <hi>Diſunion</hi> in regard of opinions <hi>which ought not to hinder the reunion of thoſe, who ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be reconciled to the Church,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">For ſo <hi>Card. Peron</hi> expreſly ſaith about <hi>num.</hi> 3</note> can not in that reſpect be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:217:10"/>a <hi>loyall ſubiect,</hi> a <hi>true Catholike,</hi> or <hi>right beleeuer;</hi> but endangereth himſelfe to be blotted out of the booke of life, and to be puniſhed in the next world with <hi>Traytors, Schiſmatikes,</hi> and <hi>Misbeleeuers,</hi> and in the meane time he will haue much adoe to cleere himſelfe in this world from the guilt, penaltie, and imputation of manifeſt <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Schiſme,</hi> and <hi>Misbeliefe:</hi> of all which crimes (beſides moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt forgerie, detraction, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering) thoſe violent hot ſpurres, that exclaim ſo bitterly againſt the Oath, and their Catholike brethren who fauour the ſame, will to their great ſhame and confuſion, ere it belong, be publikly accuſed, and in my iudgement moſt cleerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted, vnleſs they ſpeedely change their vncharitable courſes, &amp; ceaſe to make a <hi>Schiſme</hi> and diſunion among Catholikes in regard onely
<pb facs="tcp:217:11"/>of opinions, which as witneſſeth <hi>Cardinall Peron, ought not to hinder the reunion</hi> of thoſe who are not <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and <hi>ſhould deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Catholike Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 And <hi>lastly,</hi> for my owne part I proteſt vnfaignedly, that as I haue not beene affraid, in regard of the dutie &amp; obligation, wherein I ſtand bound to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to my <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and to the <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> which I profeſſe, to defend with my pen this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt truth, concerning the <hi>indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bond</hi> g of temporall <hi>Allegiance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie</hi> for the <hi>Roman Church tract'</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</note> due to our <hi>Soueraign Prince</hi> by the law of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> although I foreſaw the great diſgraces, which both in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo here in <hi>England</hi> among our <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like brethren,</hi> would come to me thereby, ſo I will (God willing) be euer readie to confirme and ſeale the ſame truth, if need ſhal require,
<pb facs="tcp:217:11"/>with my blood, vntill the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> which <hi>is the pillar &amp; ground of truth,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> (to whoſe cenſure I moſt humbly ſubmit my ſelf, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath, or ſhall be written by me) ſhall infallibly define the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, which as I am fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhe neuer will (not to ſay can not)<note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>Card. Caiet. in opaſc. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. B. virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis cap.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; Canus lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de locis cap.</hi> 3 who vpon the like grounds thinke aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly, that the Church neuer will (though <hi>Canus</hi> ſaith expreſly ſhe can not) define, that the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from original ſin.</note> define, for that in my priuate iudgement, ſpeaking with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſhe hath no ſufficient grounds, either from the holy Scriptures as they are expounded by the <hi>ancient Fathers,</hi> or from any other vndoubted rule of faith, ſo to define; but that, if ſhe will deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine either part, ſhe will declare and define according to the true and vniuerſall doctrine of the <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">See the <hi>ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> in M. <hi>Widdringt.</hi> diſcouerie of <hi>Schulke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders § 17</note> that <hi>abſolute Princes</hi> are <hi>ſupreme</hi> in temporals, &amp; therein ſubiect to none, but <hi>God</hi> alone, and alſo that the <hi>Eccleſiasticall power,</hi> by the inſtitution of <hi>Christ,</hi> doth
<pb facs="tcp:217:12"/>extend to the <hi>giuing</hi> of ſpirituall graces, not earthly kingdomes, to the <hi>remitting</hi> of ſinnes, not of debts, to the <hi>looſing</hi> of ſpirituall, not corporall bonds, to the <hi>infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting</hi> of ſpirituall, not temporall puniſhments, and to the <hi>diſpoſing</hi> of ſpirituall, not temporall goods.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>This</hi> 27 <hi>of</hi> December 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all loue, and dutie,</hi> E. I. <hi>The</hi> Author <hi>of the</hi> New-yeeres <hi>gift.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:217:12"/>
            <head>A briefe SUMMARIE OF THE CHIEFEST things contained in this ADIOYNDER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the <hi>firſt Section</hi> is ſhewed, that to proue the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> to bee vnlawfull, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonſtrations are required, but to proue it to be lawfull, only probable arguments, and anſwers are ſufficient.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſecond Section</hi> is ſhewed; <hi>Firſt,</hi> that the immediate obiect of an <hi>Oath</hi> muſt bee morally certaine to the iudgement of the Swearer, and that it neede not to be moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly certaine to all others. <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:217:13"/>that in the <hi>ſecond Branch</hi> of the Oath is denyed, both the <hi>Popes power</hi> to practiſe the depoſition of <hi>Princes,</hi> and alſo the <hi>practice</hi> it ſelfe in all caſes whatſoeuer: and that albeit the deniall of ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar practice doth not imply a deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the power it ſelfe to practiſe, yet a deniall of all practices and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, is a vertuall deniall of the power it ſelfe to practiſe. And <hi>thirdly</hi> it is ſhewed, that a meere probable power to depoſe, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh is no true, reall, lawfull, and ſufficient power, and for practiſe, as good as no power at all, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or puniſh.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>third Section</hi> is ſhewed, that euery doctrine which contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a falſhood againſt the holy Scriptures, is truely and properly hereticall, both according to the doctrine of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who hold the holy Scriptures to be the only
<pb facs="tcp:217:13"/>rule of faith, and alſo of moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines, who hold that the Church doth not make any Catholike veritie, or hereſie; but doth onely declare it, and make it knowne to all, which before her declaration was not known to all. Neither is it required in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> to make any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hereticall, that it ſubuert the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti materialis,</hi> or of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall things, which are to bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which are the generall articles of our Creede, or Chriſtian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, but that it contain a falſhood (although it be in poynts of a leſſe matter, then are the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Creed</hi>) repugnant to the Word of God, which is the rule of faith: and conſequently, ſubuerteth the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte obiecti formalis,</hi> or the formall cauſe of our beleefe, which is the infallible
<pb facs="tcp:217:14"/>truth of God, reuealed to vs in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>fourth Section</hi> is ſhewed <hi>Firſt,</hi> both by manifeſt reaſon, and alſo by the teſtimony of many learned <hi>Catholike Diuines,</hi> that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Theologicall Concluſion,</hi> which is euidently deduced from <hi>two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes,</hi> whereof <hi>the one</hi> is expreſſely contained in the Word of God, and <hi>the other</hi> manifeſt by the light of Nature, is <hi>of faith,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie <hi>hereticall,</hi> and againſt faith, and that therefore although it bee not cleare in Scriptures, <hi>expreſſely</hi> and <hi>directly,</hi> that it is manifeſt wrong to depoſe a <hi>Prince,</hi> excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and depriued by the <hi>Pope,</hi> yet it is cleere in Scriptures <hi>indirectly, vertually,</hi> and by a <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence,</hi> that it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt wrong to depoſe ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi> and conſequently to deny the ſame is properly <hi>hereticall:</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:217:14"/>that <hi>maxime</hi> of the Logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>The concluſion followeth the weaker part,</hi> is clearely explained.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>fifth Section</hi> is ſhewed; <hi>Firſt,</hi> that it is againſt the holy Scriptures <hi>indirectly, vertually,</hi> and by a <hi>neceſſarie conſequence,</hi> and therefore <hi>againſt faith,</hi> and properly <hi>hereticall,</hi> that it is lawfull to <hi>murther Princes excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, or depriued by the Pope. Secondly,</hi> that it is very falſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, to apply the doctrine of killing <hi>manifeſt Vſurpers,</hi> to the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Princes excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope;</hi> for that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Vſurpers</hi> haue no probable title to the Crowne, but <hi>Princes,</hi> after the <hi>Popes</hi> ſentence of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> and alſo <hi>depriuation,</hi> haue beſides reall poſſeſſion, a true probable title, and right to the Kingdomes, which they poſſeſſe. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that albeit a <hi>Prince</hi> ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:217:15"/>yeeld vp his <hi>Crowne</hi> after depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it were not <hi>hereticall,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my <hi>Aduerſary</hi> his grounds, to kill ſuch a Prince, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my <hi>Aduerſary</hi> doth grant it to be euident murther, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>vertually</hi> repugnant to the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſixth Section</hi> is ſhewed <hi>Firſt,</hi> that the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres Gift</hi> did not bring thoſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi> of taking a purſe from one, who leadeth a wicked life, or kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him with a piſtoll, to compare them to the depoſing, or murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Princes excommunicated, or depriued by the Pope; but hee brought them onely to proue, that to make a particular propoſition to be hereticall, it ſufficeth, that it be contained in the generall propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is expreſſed in the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> ſo that it be ſufficiently proued, to bee contained therein.
<pb facs="tcp:217:15"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the compariſon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe had beene apt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to proue, that to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctrine hereticall it ſufficeth, that it bee indirectly, vertually, or by a neceſſarie conſequence, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the holy Scriptures. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that no Catholike Writer, except onely <hi>Suarez,</hi> durſt euer aduenture to teach expreſſely, that a Prince after depriuation, may by the Popes commiſſion be killed by any priuate man; but becauſe this pernicious doctrine of <hi>Suarez</hi> is grounded vpon a moſt falſe and abſurd ſuppoſition, and which all the world ſeeth to bee falſe and abſurd, to wit, that the doctrine for the Popes power to depoſe and murther wicked Princes, is moſt certaine and of faith, and out of all controuerſie among learned Catholikes, his doctrine being grounded vpon a ſuppoſition ſo
<pb facs="tcp:217:16"/>manifeſtly falſe &amp; abſurd, cannot by any Catholike bee accounted probable.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſeuenth Section</hi> is ſhewed, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> explication of thoſe words <hi>[depoſe, or murther]</hi> being grounded vpon the nature of a conditionall diſiunctiue, is true, proper, and agreeable to the common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of the words, nor repugnant to <hi>His Maieſties</hi> intention, albeit M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> doth not rely onely vpon that explication.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>eighth Section</hi> is ſhewed, that according to the doctrine of many learned Catholike Diuines, and manifeſt reaſon, that rule of the Law, <hi>In the like caſe the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poſſeſſour is the better,</hi> ought to be vnderſtood, not onely of a true doubt, and when the minde doth fluctuate, and giueth no aſſent to either part, but alſo of
<pb facs="tcp:217:16"/>a probable doubt; neither can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man with reaſon imagine, that when both parts haue probability, the caſe is not therein alike.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ninth Section</hi> is ſhewed, that a <hi>Prince</hi> in keeping his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to which he hath a probable title or right, doth neither wrong the <hi>Pope, Church,</hi> or any other, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that vulgar maxime, <hi>He that vſeth his own right, doth no man wrong,</hi> nor hindereth vniuſtly any greater good, and the ſame is in the beginning of the next <hi>Section</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a moſt manifeſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ad hominem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Tenth Section</hi> is ſhewed, that according to <hi>Vaſques</hi> doctrin, which he thinketh to be certaine, and the contrarie falſe, <hi>improbable, abſurd,</hi> and <hi>pernicious,</hi> it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any Prince onely vpon a probable title to make war againſt an other Prince, who hath not only
<pb facs="tcp:217:17"/>a probable title, but alſo poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But this queſtion is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to the matter of this preſent Oath, and to the right, which Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may pretend to make warre vpon probable titles, which are grounded vpon the Popes power to depoſe Princes, as it is more at large declared in the thirteenth <hi>Section.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>eleuenth</hi> and <hi>twelfth Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is ſhewed, that a <hi>Prince,</hi> in keeping his poſſeſſion, to which he hath a probable right or title, doth no man wrong, nor hindreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly any greater good, and that although a probable title be good for ſomething, and in ſome caſes better then no title at all, yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as concerneth the making of warre againſt him who hath both a probable title, and alſo poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is in <hi>Vaſques</hi> doctrine, which he thinketh to be certaine, as good
<pb facs="tcp:217:17"/>as no title, although we ſuppoſe the title to be meerely temporall, but if the title be grounded vpon a probable ſpirituall authoritie, in all learned mens iudgement, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the approued grounds of Diuinitie, it is as good, as no title at all, which is at large confirmed in the <hi>thirteenth Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>thirteenth Section</hi> is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a manifeſt diſparitie betwixt the lawfulneſſe of making warre vpon probable titles, which are meerely temporall, and which are grounded vpon a probable ſpirituall authoritie, for that there is no aſſured and infallible way on earth to decide, or know vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, by way of ſentence and iudgement, the truth of meere temporall titles, which are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie betwixt two abſolute Princes, who in meere temporall
<pb facs="tcp:217:18"/>affaires are ſubiect to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſentence of none but God alone, but <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his Church an infallible way to decide, and know vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the truth of all titles, which are grounded vpon whatſoeuer pretended ſpirituall authoritie, to wit, the determination and deciſion of a lawfull and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted generall Councell: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is cleerely inferred, that albeit Princes might lawfully make warre vpon probable titles which bee meerely temporall, becauſe there is no way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controuerſie but by war, yet they can not lawfully make warre vpon probable titles, which are grounded vpon a probable ſpirituall authoritie, becauſe Chriſt hath left in his Church an infallible and peaceable way to decide certainely by way of
<pb facs="tcp:217:18"/>ſentence and iudgement, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making of warre, the truth of all ſuch doubtfull and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſed titles, which infallible and peaceable way he hath now left to decide by way of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and iudgement, the truth and certainety of probable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, which are meerely tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>fourteenth Section</hi> is ſhewed, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> laſt Explication of thoſe words <hi>[as hereticall]</hi> is true and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and agreeable to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence and vnderſtanding of the words, nor repugnant to <hi>His Maiesties</hi> intention, although he doe not rely onely vpon that Explication.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>fifteenth Section</hi> is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the obligation of all <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue Breues,</hi> as well belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to faith, as manners, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:217:19"/>vpon the fundamentall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; former precept, which they ſuppoſe and declare, and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> forbidding the Oath, for that it <hi>containeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things flat contrarie to faith and ſaluation,</hi> which is the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reaſon of his declaratiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, haue not force to bind, becauſe this fundamentall reaſon is grounded vpon two ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are manifeſtly falſe, to wit, that the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> is denied in the Oath, and that his authoritie to <hi>depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> is an vndoubted point of faith, nor in controuerſie among lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Catholikes.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>ſixteenth Section</hi> is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>ſixt Branch</hi> of the Oath is lawfull, to wit, that <hi>the Oath is ministred by good and full authoritie,</hi> euen to thoſe Catholikes, who are perſwaded the Oath to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:217:19"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Last Section</hi> is ſhewed, that the <hi>last Branch</hi> of the Oath is lawful, for that euerie good &amp; loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubiect may and ought to take it very <hi>willingly,</hi> although great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties be impoſed againſt thoſe, who refuſe to take the ſame: And laſtly the <hi>Author,</hi> who hath brought theſe exceptions againſt the Oath, is friendly admoniſhed not to make any Schiſme or Diſunion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Engliſh Catholikes, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending that doctrine, <hi>which the Pope himſelfe tolerateth in France,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>So ſatth</hi> Card. Peron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Harangue auſtiers eſtat. pag. <hi>94.</hi> Card. Peron <hi>in his laſt great</hi> Reply cap. <hi>91.</hi> pag. <hi>633.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>which</hi> (as <hi>Card. Peron</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth) <hi>ought not hinder the reunion of thoſe, who ſhould deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the Church,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing that it hath been by many publike <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France</hi> approued, &amp; the contrary doctrine vnder <hi>paine</hi> of <hi>Treaſon</hi> condemned, for <hi>falſe, perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſcandalous,</hi> and <hi>ſedicious.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:217:20"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:217:20"/>
            <head>The <hi>Copy</hi> of a letter written by <hi>R. P.</hi> a religious <hi>Catholike</hi> Prieſt to <hi>M. B.</hi> a very learned <hi>Roman Catholike,</hi> in anſwer to certaine difficulties obiected by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd <hi>M. B.</hi> againſt the late Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>New-yeares Gift,</hi> or <hi>Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegeance.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was left for mee, in the end of the laſt <hi>Trinity Term,</hi> &amp; in my abſence, a letter with this ſuperſcription, <hi>[To the worſhipfull, and his moſt reſpected friend E. I. giue theſe]</hi> and the Partie who brought it, ſayd, it was ſent and meant for me. Which after I had ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and peruſed the firſt beginning thereof, I was a little greeued in this reſpect, that a friend, and old acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:217:21"/>of mine, ſhould ſeeke, as then I conceiued, to put a tricke vpon me, in making mee to bee the <hi>Author</hi> of the late <hi>New-yeeres Gift,</hi> whereas the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> thereof (knowing belike how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſuch bookes are in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) was deſirous (as you might haue gathered by the <hi>Inſcription</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) to haue his name concealed. Whereupon ſome friends, to whom I ſhewed your letter, endeuoured to perſwade mee not to meddle at all therewith, but to returne it backe to the Party, who brought it. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, becauſe I did not attribute this your errour to any euill affection, or meaning in you towards me, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſome want of diſcretion, or conſideration in you, and for that as it ſeemeth, you are deſirous to haue <hi>from me</hi> ſome anſwer to your obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I my ſelfe, hauing alſo read and peruſed the ſaid <hi>New-yeeres Gift</hi> with all diligence, and not diſliking the grounds and principles therof (which I am not affraid publikely to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) will in regard of our old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, without more adoe, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:217:21"/>ſeeking any other Reply from <hi>E. I.</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> thereof, take the paines to anſwer, according to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> grounds, to the principall obiections contained in your letter, which I will entirely, <hi>ad verbum,</hi> and orderly ſet downe, onely diuiding it into certaine parts, or <hi>Sections,</hi> without altering, or inuerting the order of your letter. Thus therefore you begin.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 1. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>1. WOrthy Sir, and mine old acquaintance: Hauing read and peruſed with all diligence, your late booke for the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> mee thinketh I finde not in it that fulneſſe of ſatisfaction, at the least in all poynts, which was expected, and I and others could haue wiſhed. And therefore I make bold (preſuming of our ancient amitie) to trouble you with ſome few lines, concerning the chiefe doubts and difficulties I finde about your booke, and expoſition of the Oath. Blame me not <hi>(good Sir)</hi> that I make thus bold to trouble you in this buſineſſe;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:217:22"/>for it is a matter, which concerneth much both my ſelfe and others, and ſuch indeed as requireth great diſcuſſion, and moſt diligent examination. If the Oath might lawfully bee taken, as you labour to proue, and (whatſoeuer others think) as I am perſwaded, with great ſincerity, zeale to God, and loue to your Prince and Countrey, I ſhould bee glad, and none more glad; for it would yeeld great content to our Prince, (a thing much to bee wiſhed of all louing and loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects) and no ſmall comfort to our poore afflicted brethren, wearied and almoſt waſted to nothing, for refuſall of the ſame. But if it cannot (as I much feare) at the leaſt in that ſenſe it is exacted at our hands, no maruell if wee, who haue daily to deale with poore mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, labour what wee can, to haue it throughly examined. And this I would haue you aſſure your ſelfe, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſcruple or doubt you ſhall finde, that I doe make about your doctrine, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Oath, I will not doe it of any euill affection, contradictious ſpirit, or humour to wrangle (for of that ſort there hath been too much ſayd, and done
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:217:22"/>already, and a happy attonement were heartily to bee wiſhed) but meerely for loue of truth, and deſire of ſatisfaction to poore afflicted conſciences, which through the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> on the one ſide, together with many other ſtiffe defenders of that doctrine, and your late <hi>expoſition</hi> of the Oath, and the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof on the other, ſtill, God not, remaine perplexed, and hardly know yet what to doe.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT <hi>firſt,</hi> I doe not well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, what <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of <hi>ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in all points</hi> you did expect, and haue not found in the late <hi>New-yeeres Gift.</hi> For if you expected, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> from whom the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres Gift,</hi> hath collected his <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> ſhould haue taken vpon him in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie of the <hi>Oath,</hi> (which is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> though vpon falſe informations and ſuppoſitions, and alſo impugned by diuerſe learned men vpon the ſame falſe grounds) to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:217:23"/>proue it to bee lawfull by ſuch cleare and euident demonſtrations, as that no wrangling ſpirit, or ſtiffe Impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Oath, could alledge any doubt, difficulty, or ſcruple againſt his arguments, or anſwers; you were herein greatly miſtaken, neither had you any reaſon to expect the ſame: eſpecially if you had duely conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what he did obſerue in his <hi>Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Diſputation</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">In the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> n. 4.</note>; both for that to bring ſuch euident demonſtrations in any controuerſie whatſoeuer among learned Catholikes, is a very hard matter; and alſo becauſe it was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for him to anſwer probably all the arguments, which could bee brought againſt the <hi>Oath,</hi> and to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſuch probable proofes, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded both vpon the cleare principles of <hi>Philoſophie, Law,</hi> and <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> and alſo vpon the teſtimony, authority, and confeſſion of his <hi>chiefeſt Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> which might perſwade any pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, learned, and indifferent man, that there is nothing in the Oath, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to faith, or ſaluation,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that it may with a ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:217:23"/>bee taken. And whether hee hath ſufficiently performed this, or no, the learned Reader muſt iudge, &amp; you your ſelf, by the anſwers to your doubts, difficulties, or rather, as you well tearme them, <hi>ſcruples,</hi> may eaſily perceiue.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I cannot blame you, for labouring to haue this controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the <hi>Oath,</hi> to bee throughly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, conſidering it doth ſo neerely concerne our duty to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and conſequently, the ſpiritual ſafety, or hurt to our ſoules (to omit now all temporall loſſes) by taking or refuſing the ſame. But truely, in my conceit, if without all partiality, or ouermuch affection to either part, you would be as curious and carefull to finde out fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable <hi>Expoſitions</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> as you haue beene to inuent doubts, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, or rather <hi>ſcriples</hi> againſt the ſame, you would eaſily perceiue, that no conuincing and demonſtratiue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument can be brought, to proue the <hi>Oath</hi> vnlawfull. And the variety, and diuerſity of the grounds, whereupon the ſtiffe Impugners therof do chiefly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:217:24"/>inſiſt, ſome diſprouing the Oath for this clauſe, ſome for another, ſome for this reaſon, others not for that, ſome for the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> others not daring to ground themſelues on them, and few agreeing among themſelues in any one point (beſides the ſilence, both of the <hi>Popes Holineſſe,</hi> in not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing as yet any one clauſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the <hi>Oath,</hi> which is cleerely <hi>repugnant to faith, or ſaluation,</hi> although he hath beene often moſt humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted to declare the ſame, and the ſilence alſo of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt aduerlaries, to whom hee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, who, as it ſeemeth, haue left him in the open field) and moreouer, the weakneſſe of your doubts and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, which, after ſo long a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion of this controuerſie, as the moſt principall obiections, you haue ſingled from the reſt, doe ſufficiently confirme, that no conuincing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can bee brought to proue the <hi>Oath</hi> vnlawfull. Now to your <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:217:24"/>
               <head>Sect. 2. Obiection.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>VVEll then (good Sir) the first difficultie that I find,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> is about your doctrine in the Expoſition of the first Branch <hi>(you would ſay the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Branch)</hi> of the Oath, how it can be true, which you ſeeme to teach, That we may lawfully ſweare not only our acknowledgement, but alſo the abſolute propoſition, <hi>That the Pope hath no authoritie to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> when the contradictorie propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, <hi>That the Pope hath that authoritie,</hi> is probable, and holden for ſuch not only by the ancient Schoole-Diuines &amp; Caſuists, who might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture not haue marked all your grounds, but alſo by our own moderne Doctors, who, no doubt, haue ſeen the reaſons, and examined the grounds on both parts, when, as you know, the matter of an Oath ought to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and when one part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictorie is probable, the other can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be certaine.</p>
                  <p>I marke well, how you ſay, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:217:25"/>of this difficultie, that in the Oath you ſweare, <hi>That the Pope hath no authoritie to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> not meaning it ſpeculatiuè, <hi>in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation or conceipt,</hi> but practicè, <hi>for as much as concerneth practiſe:</hi> which is as much as to ſay, you doe not ſweare, that the Pope hath no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to depoſe Princes, but that he can practiſe no ſuch power vpon any Prince being in poſſeſſion, ſo long as it is but probable, the Pope hath that power; and this alwaies is most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, grounded on that rule, In pari caſu melior est conditio poſſidentis, <hi>In the like caſe the condition of the poſſeſſour is the better;</hi> and ſo may be the matter of an Oath, and lawfully ſworne:</p>
                  <p>But this in my conceipt will not ſerue the turne, for that the words in the Oath in their proper ſignification can haue no ſuch meaning, but doe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, that we ſweare not only that the Pope can practiſe no ſuch power and authoritie, but that he hath no ſuch power. And although Princes, or priuate men, doe little regard what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:217:25"/>learned men do <hi>ſpeculatiuè in ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> dispute, or teach in Schooles concerning their titles, ſo they may be ſecured of their estates, yet when the words of the Oath in this Branch in their proper ſignification import a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of the power, and not of the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; and the controuerſie betwixt Popes and Princes hath euer beene of the power, and not of the practiſe; and when by the <hi>Seuenth Branch</hi> we are tyed to take the words of the Oath in their proper ſignification, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their common ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I can not ſee, how this Clauſe abſolutely (making the denyall of the Popes power to depoſe Princes the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Obiect of the Oath) may be ſworne without periurie; Eſpecially ſeeing it is most likely, that the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law-maker was, that wee ſhould by this Oath abiure not only the practiſe of this power, but rather the power it ſelf, which both might be and had been the roote and origine of the practiſe of ſuch power; which if it were not, it were graciouſly don of our Prince, to declare his intention to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:217:26"/>otherwiſe, that his Catholike ſubiects might know, how to comport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in theſe affaires: For his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates, and Officers, appointed to ſee this Law executed, doe ſeeme to inſinuate euerie where, that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Prince and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth is, that not onely the practiſe, but alſo the power ſhould be abiured; And therefore if any chance to take this Oath vpon frailtie or otherwiſe, they will not ſticke to tell him in open audience, that he hath abiured the Popes power, and conſequently his faith<note n="b" place="margin">As <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> and other <hi>Ieſuits</hi> haue very falſly &amp; ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the Popes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be a point of faith.</note>.</p>
               </q>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt this <hi>firſt</hi> difficultie of yours is eaſily anſwered. And <hi>first,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the matter of an Oath ought to be <hi>certain,</hi> yet it is to be vnderſtood of the <hi>immediate matter,</hi> or obiect of the Oath, and alſo of <hi>morall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie,</hi> and that alſo not in reſpect of all men, but in reſpect only of the ſwearer, or, according to the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iudgement of the ſwearer, as hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:217:26"/>been ſufficiently declared in the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeeres gift;</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">In the <hi>firſt</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation</note> for the ſame thing may be certain, or probable to the iudgement of one, which is not certaine, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable to the iudgement of an other. From whence theſe <hi>two</hi> things may be inferred.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The <hi>one,</hi> that <hi>Becanus</hi> houlding for certain,<note place="margin">Becanus in controuerſia Anglicana anno dom. <hi>1612.</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſa pag. <hi>102</hi>
                     </note> that King <hi>Iames</hi> is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraign Lord in temporals of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, might lawfully ſweare the ſame, although ſome others improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hould, that the <hi>Pope</hi> and not King <hi>Iames</hi> is the Soueraigne Lord in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals thereof. And <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſques</hi> houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for certaine, that it is not lawfull ſo make warre vpon a probable title againſt a Prince, who hath not onely a probable title, but alſo poſſeſſion (for he affirmeth,<note n="d" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>ſect.</hi> 10 <hi>num.</hi> 2.</note> that the contrarie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hath in his iudgement no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie at all) might lawfully ſweare the ſame. And likewiſe they who hould it for certain, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no lawfull power or authoritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes, or, which is all one to practiſe their depoſition, may lawfully ſweare the ſame. And the reaſon is,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:217:27"/>for that the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritie,</hi> which is required in an Oath, is not to be taken from the thing ſworn, as it is in it ſelfe, or <hi>a parte rei,</hi> but as it is in the vnderſtanding of him that ſweareth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The <hi>other,</hi> which may be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is, that if the <hi>immediate obiect</hi> of this <hi>ſecond Branch</hi> of the Oath be not this abſolute propoſition, <hi>That the Pope hath not any authoritie to depoſe the King &amp;c.</hi> (as it hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proued by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> and alſo your ſilence, in not impugning that firſt Explication of his, ſeemeth to confirme the ſame) then by this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultly of yours it can not bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proued, that this <hi>ſecond Branch</hi> of the Oath is vnlawfull: for when <hi>two anſwerers</hi> are giuen to <hi>one obiection</hi> it is neceſſarie to confute them both, to proue the obiection to be of force.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But <hi>ſecondly</hi> it is manifeſt, that alſo M. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> ſecond Explication of this Branch is very true, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your obiection againſt the ſame. For all the force of your diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie conſiſteth in your falſe gloſſing of thoſe words, <hi>The Pope hath no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:217:27"/>or authoritie, practicè</hi> (that is for as much as concerneth practiſe) <hi>to depoſe Princes: Which is as much as to ſay</hi> (ſay you) <hi>we doe not ſweare, that the Pope hath no authoritie to depoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but that he can practiſe no ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vpon any Prince being in poſſeſſion, as long as it is but probable, that the Pope hath that power.</hi> But this Gloſſe of yours is very vntrue, and alſo expreſly repugnant to the words themſelues. For the plain meaning of theſe words, <hi>The Pope hath no power or authoritie practicè</hi> (that is for practiſe) <hi>to depoſe Princes,</hi> is, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no <hi>true, reall, ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>lawfull</hi> power, or authoritie to practiſe the depoſition of Princes, at any time, for any cauſe, crime or end whatſoeuer. And beſides M. <hi>Widdrington</hi> ſaith in expres words, <hi>That the Pope hath no power or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to depoſe,</hi> or practiſe the depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Princes, and not onely, <hi>that hee can not practiſe their depoſition,</hi> or, which is all one, depoſe them: as though you would haue him to grant, that the Pope hath a <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>lawful</hi> power and authoritie to depoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:217:28"/>Princes, but that he can not <hi>lawfully</hi> or without ſin <hi>practiſe</hi> this his authority.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Moreouer,</hi> I can not perceiue any difference in ſubſtance and effect, betwixt theſe two propoſitions, which you would ſeeme to diſtinguiſh, <hi>The Pope hath no power or authoritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes,</hi> or to practiſe their depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and, <hi>The Pope can not practiſe any ſuch power or authoritie to depoſe vpon any Prince,</hi> ſeeing that whoſoeuer denieth all effects of any power, doth vertually and in effect deny the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it ſelf, <hi>Frustra enim est illa potestas, &amp; proinde nulla (cùm Deus &amp; Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra nihil faciant frustra) quae nunquam reducitur adactum:</hi> for <hi>that power is vaine or idle (ſeeing that God and Nature doth no thing idly or in vaine) which is neuer brought to act.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Suarez</hi> from thoſe words of the third Branch <hi>[notwithstanding any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of depriuation or abſolution of the ſubiects from their allegiance, made or to be made &amp;c. I will beare faith and true allegiance to his Maiestie &amp;c.]</hi> doth well conclude a denyall of the <hi>Popes power</hi> to depriue Prince, and to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:217:28"/>abſolue ſubiects from their allegiance, to be <hi>vertually</hi> conteyned in thoſe words, for that the denial of all effects of any power doth imply a deniall of the power it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Wherefore if M. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> and the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeres gift,</hi> had denyed the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Popes power</hi> only in ſome particular caſes, as M. <hi>Blackwell</hi> did at the firſt deny the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Popes power</hi> to depoſe the King, for that <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibus, things ſtanding as they doe at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> the Pope could not, without great hurt to Engliſh Catholikes, <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> vpon him his pretended <hi>power</hi> to depoſe Princes, and thereupon did ill conclude, that the Pope had no <hi>power</hi> nor <hi>authoritie to depoſe the King,</hi> then indeed you might wel infer, that they did only deny the <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Popes power to depoſe,</hi> but not the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authoritie</hi> it ſelfe, which is repugnant to his <hi>Maieſties</hi> meaning, who by this Branch of the Oath intended to deny the <hi>Popes authoritie to practiſe</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, in any caſe, or for any cauſe, crime, or end whatſoeuer, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:217:29"/>to deny, not only the <hi>practiſe,</hi> but alſo the <hi>power it ſelfe.</hi> But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that they in expreſſe tearmes deny both the <hi>Popes power</hi> &amp; <hi>authority</hi> to <hi>practiſe</hi> the depoſition of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie,</hi> and conſequently of any other Prince not directly ſubiect to the Pope in temporals, &amp; alſo the <hi>practiſe</hi> thereof in all caſes whatſoeuer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the crime ſhould deſerue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and the Pope ſhould haue ſufficient forces, and alſo conuenient meanes to put in execution his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of depriuation, truly you had no reaſon, nor colour of reaſon to ſay, that they denied onely the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Popes power to depoſe,</hi> but not the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authoritie it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. But becauſe you ſhall ſee, that my meaning is not to conceale, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure any difficultie, I will vrge this obiection of yours againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> ſomewhat more forcibly in forme and ſhew, than you haue done, in this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſoeuer acknowledgeth, that the Pope hath ſome power and authoritie to depoſe Princes, cannot lawfully ſweare,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:217:29"/>nor acknowledge by oath, that the Pope hath not any power, or authority to depoſe them. But</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Widdrington <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, that the Pope hath ſome power and authority to depoſe Princes: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot lawfully ſweare, or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by oath, that the Pope hath not any power, or authority, to depoſe them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> is manifeſt, for that in ſo ſwearing, he ſhould commit mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt periurie, in ſwearing, or acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging by oath that to be true, which he acknowledgeth to bee falſe, ſeeing that to haue <hi>ſome authoritie,</hi> and <hi>not to haue any authority,</hi> are <hi>contradictories.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> is proued thus: <hi>A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable power to depoſe is ſome power; But</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Widdrington <hi>acknowledgeth, that the Pope hath a probable power,</hi> ſaltem ſpeculatiuè, <hi>at leaſt in ſpeculation, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Therefore hee acknowledgeth, that hee hath ſome power to depoſe;</hi> And yet in the Oath wee muſt ſweare, or at leaſt acknowledge by oath, <hi>That the Pope hath not any power, or authority, to depoſe the King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. But this obiection is eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. For the true meaning of thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:217:30"/>words, <hi>That the Pope hath not any power or authority, to depoſe,</hi> &amp;c, according to their plaine, proper, and vſuall ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the intention of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty,</hi> is, that the Pope hath not any <hi>true, reall, ſufficient,</hi> and <hi>lawfull power,</hi> or authoritie to <hi>depoſe,</hi> &amp;c. But a <hi>meere probable power</hi> to depoſe, is no <hi>true, reall, ſufficient,</hi> or <hi>lawfull power,</hi> but for practiſe and effect it is only an <hi>imaginarie power,</hi> or a <hi>power</hi> in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and imagination of ſome Doctors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> but in very deed, and for practiſe &amp; effect it is no <hi>true, reall, lawfull power</hi> at all, or which may bee a <hi>ſufficient ground to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> For euery power hath relation to the effect, and where there can bee no reall and lawfull effect, or practice, there is no reall and lawfull power to practiſe; for power, and effect, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, are correlatiues, and one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth vpon the other. And this is ſo plaine and manifeſt, that there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no declaration of his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> to explaine the ſame. And therefore I wiſh you to remember, that when the words of penall Lawes may, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their proper and vſuall ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:217:30"/>be expounded in a fauourable ſenſe, wee ought not, contrarie to the rules preſcribed by Diuines, for the interpreting of lawes, ſeeke to wreſt them to an abſurd and inconuenient ſenſe. Neither can any man, with any colour of reaſon imagin, that his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie</hi> would haue vs to ſweare, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that, which hee himſelfe knoweth to be vntrue, to wit, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any power or authority to depoſe, ſo much as in the conceit, imagination, and opinion of ſome Catholikes, yea and of the <hi>Pope</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but his meaning is, to haue vs to ſweare, or at leaſt acknowledge by Oath, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no <hi>true, reall,</hi> and <hi>lawfull power to depoſe,</hi> and which may be a <hi>ſufficient ground</hi> and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to <hi>practiſe</hi> the depoſition of any <hi>abſolute Prince,</hi> notwithſtanding this their <hi>conceit, imagination,</hi> or <hi>opinion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. But perchance you will <hi>obiect,</hi> that both the <hi>power to depoſe,</hi> and alſo the <hi>practice</hi> it ſelfe is approued for <hi>lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and <hi>ſufficient,</hi> not onely by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Schoole-Diuines, <hi>who peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (as you inſinuate aboue) <hi>might not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:217:31"/>haue marked all</hi> Widdringtons <hi>grounds, but alſo by our owne moderne Doctours, who no doubt haue ſeene the reaſons, and examined the grounds on both parts,</hi> therefore the <hi>Pope</hi> hath at leaſt wiſe a <hi>probable, lawfull,</hi> and <hi>ſufficient power</hi> to <hi>practiſe</hi> the depoſition of Princes. But this <hi>obiection</hi> hath beene anſwered at large in the <hi>Neweyeares Gift</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>num.</hi> 9.</note> For thoſe <hi>Doctors,</hi> who approue the <hi>practice</hi> of depoſing Princes by the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, doe ground their doctrine vpon a very falſe principle, and which all the world now ſeeth to bee falſe and abſurd, to wit, that it is certaine and vnqueſtionable among Catholikes, that the Pope hath authoritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes; or elſe they did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the manifeſt difference betwixt the <hi>lawfull practiſe</hi> of a <hi>probable power</hi> concerning <hi>fauour,</hi> and <hi>puniſhment.</hi> But that doctrine ought not to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>probable</hi> in reſpect of extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall grounds, or the authority of Doctors, when it is grounded vpon a principle, which is knowne to bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly falſe, as is this, that it is not now a controuerſie among Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:217:31"/>whether the Pope hath authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to depoſe <hi>Princes,</hi> or no. Neither can you alledge any one ancient, or moderne Doctour, who holding the doctrine, for the Popes power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Princes, to bee but <hi>probable,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth the practice thereof to bee lawfull. For which cauſe they haue ſo much laboured theſe latter yeeres, to proue it to bee certaine, and of faith, but all in vaine. And therefore they haue now thought it beſt to bee ſilent, then to write any more of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, leſt their further writings proue the doctrine, which they in times paſt would haue had to be certaine, to bee now ſcarſe <hi>probable.</hi> Yet I cannot but commend the ingenuity of <hi>Becanus,</hi> who although ſome yeeres paſt was as hot in this queſtion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Becanus</hi> in Tract. de fide. ca. 15. q 4.</note> as any of the reſt; for before hee affirmed, that <hi>it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine at the leaſt,</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">In <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſia Anglic.</hi> cha. 3. q. 3.</note> that the Pope hath authority to depoſe Princes, yet now hauing ſome occaſion to treat thereof againe, is content to leaue it as a <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie,</hi> or controuerſie. <hi>Certum eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is certaine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that if we regard onely the Law of God, or Nature, hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:217:32"/>Princes are not depriued of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, or Iuriſdiction,</hi> de facto: <hi>But whether a Prince may, by the Law of the Church, and the Popes ſentence, be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of his Dominion and Iuriſdiction, it is a difficulty.</hi> And therefore <hi>Card. Peron</hi> now in his laſt booke, cap. 91. p. 633. expreſſely affirmeth, <hi>That this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie</hi> ought not <hi>to hinder the re-vnion of thoſe, who ſhould bee reconciled to the Church.</hi> In ſo much, that he laboreth alſo to excuſe <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> and ſayth, that <hi>Card. Bellarmine hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed his Readers, that what hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, concerning the Popes power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly in temporals, he did not propound it as a doctrine of faith, and whereof wee muſt needs hold the one part, or the other, vnder paine of Excommunication, and Anathema:</hi> which is as much as to ſay, that albeit <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> did hold it to be a doctrine of faith, yet he did hold it to bee ſo onely in his owne priuate opinion, which others of the contrary opinion were not bound to follow vnder paine of <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Anathema.</hi> As likewiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> in times paſt held
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:217:32"/>their doctrine <hi>de auxilijs gratiae,</hi> to bee of faith; yet becauſe they held it to bee ſo onely in their priuate opinion, they knew right well, that the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans,</hi> who held the contrary, were not bound to follow their priuate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, vnder pain of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>Anathema:</hi> and therfore they did not thereby cauſe a Schiſme in the Church, by ſeeking to exclude them from Sacraments, and Eccleſiaſticall Communion. Neither ought they now, according to <hi>Card. Peron</hi> his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, proceed otherwiſe in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie of the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depoſe Princes.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. And if you <hi>obiect</hi> again, which you vrge beneath, Sect. 11. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a <hi>probable title,</hi> that if a probable power to depoſe and puniſh, bee not a ſufficient and lawfull power to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, it is as good as no power at all. I <hi>anſwer,</hi> that for as much as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth practice, it is in very deed as good as no power at all, for that a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable power</hi> cannot bee a ſufficient ground to puniſh, or depriue any man of that which he poſſeſſeth, as <hi>Leſſius,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:217:33"/>and <hi>P. Kellinſon</hi> well obſerued, yet ſpeaking generally your conſequence is not good, for no power is good for nothing, but a probable power to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and depoſe, is good for this, to haue the matter examined by a lawful and vndoubted Iudge, who in reſpect of the deciding of the Popes power to depoſe Princes, can onely be a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vndoubted Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, as hath beene declared ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>New-yeeres Gift.</hi> And this may ſuffice for the cleering of this difficulty.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 3. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>SEcondly I finde <hi>(ſay you)</hi> another difficulty about your expoſition of the fourth Branch; for I cannot ſee, how any with ſafety of conſcience can ſwear, that the doctrine, which maintaineth, <hi>That Princes which be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated and depriued, may bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or murthered by their owne ſubiects, &amp;c.</hi> is impious and hereticall, though wee ſhould take <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſenſe, which you doe take it (which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:217:33"/>yet in my conceit is not ſo proper with vs, nor Proteſtants, who moſt of them hold that for hereticall, which ſubuerteth the foundation of faith, and not that which is contrarie to Scripture.)</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT before I goe any further,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> to ſet downe and examine the proofes of what here you ſay, it is ſtrange to mee, that a man of your learning and reading ſhould conceiue, that the taking of <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſenſe, wherein <hi>Widdrington</hi> doth take it, to wit, for that falſe doctrine, which is contrary to the holy Scriptures, is not ſo proper neither with vs, nor <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> For the Proteſtants hold the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to bee the onely rule of ſaith, and conſequently that to bee <hi>hereticall,</hi> or againſt faith, which is contrary to the Word of God, which is the rule of faith. And therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>falſhood,</hi> which is repugnant to the Word, and teſtimony of God contained in the holy Scriptures, is in the doctrine of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and alſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:217:34"/>of the moſt <hi>Catholike Diuines, hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and repugnant to diuine and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall faith, though it be only in a poynt of ſome hiſtoricall narration, as to deny,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euod.</hi> 3.</note> that <hi>God appeared to Moyſes in a flame of fire out of the mids of a buſh,</hi> &amp; <hi>that the buſh burned with fire, &amp; was not conſumed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</note> or to deny that <hi>Iob</hi> had <hi>ſeuen ſons, and three daughters,</hi> or ſuch like: for albeit theſe, and ſuch like falſhoods, doe not directly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely ſubuert the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte credendorum,</hi> in regard of the materiall obiect of ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall faith, which is principally contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Creed,</hi> yet they ſubuert the foundation of faith, <hi>ex parte regulae fidei,</hi> and in regard of the formall obiect of faith, which is the infallible truth and teſtimony of God reuealed to vs in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and ſo the auerring of theſe faſhoods make God a Lyar, and doe indirectly, vertually, and by a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequence ſubuert the <hi>firſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of our <hi>Creede,</hi> and deſtroy the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power, knowledge, or goodnes of <hi>God,</hi> and conſequently <hi>God himſelfe,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:217:34"/>and therefore are truely and properly <hi>hereticall</hi> falſhoods, or repugnant to faith, both according to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and moſt learned <hi>Catholike Diuines.</hi> Whereupon all Diuines commonly doe put in the <hi>firſt</hi> place, or degree of hereticall propoſitions, thoſe which are expreſſely and formally againſt the holy Scriptures, and in <hi>ſecond,</hi> or <hi>third</hi> place thoſe, which are repugnant to the definitions of the Church. See Cardinall <hi>Turrecremata</hi> in Sum. de Eccleſia lib. 4. part. 2. cap. 10. <hi>Canus</hi> lib. 12. de locis cap. 7. <hi>Bannes</hi> 2 <hi>a</hi> 2 <hi>ae.</hi> q. 11. ar. 2. <hi>Franciſcus</hi> de <hi>Chriſto</hi> diſt. 25. in. q. 3. de haereſi, in Excurſu de Catholica veritate. <hi>Directorium Inquit ſitorum</hi> part. 2. comment. 27. in prima regula, beſides <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro,</hi> and <hi>Couerruuias,</hi> cited by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> in his anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> part. 2. Append. p. 69.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Veritas Catholica est veritas,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith <hi>Franciſcus à Chriſto) Catholike verity is a verity deliuered ſupernatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and made known by God alone; Wherof there are foure kindes. The firſt kinde is of thoſe truths, or verities, which are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:217:35"/>and expreſſely contained in the holy Scriptures.</hi> And beneath ſaith hee: <hi>Therefore the firſt degree of hereticall propoſitions is of thoſe, which are againſt Catholike verity, or truth contained for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally &amp; expreſſely in the holy Scriptures.</hi> The ſame ſaith <hi>Turrecremata</hi> in the places aboue cited.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Catholicae veritates illae habendae ſunt,</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith <hi>Franciſcus Pegna</hi> in Comment. 27. vpon the <hi>Directorie</hi> of the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> part. 2.) <hi>Catholike verities are to be accounted thoſe, which are contained in the holy Scripture of the old and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi> And a little aboue in q. 2. <hi>Illa propoſitio</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That propoſition is hee reticall</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eymericus,</hi> whom <hi>Pegna</hi> gloſſeth) <hi>which is againſt the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture approued by the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. And therefore (as well ſayth <hi>Card. Turrecremata</hi> cap. 3.) <hi>Eccleſiae determinatio</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The determination of the Church doth not make, nor can make hereſie, or an hereticall propoſition, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catholike verity: becauſe, as Cas tholike verities without all approbation of the Church; of their owne nature are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, and immutably true, ſo immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:217:35"/>they are to be accounted Catholike: And likewiſe, hereſies without all condens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Church are hereſies.</hi> The ſame ſaith <hi>Caſtro</hi> and <hi>Couerruuias</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Widdrington</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">In his <hi>Appendix</hi> to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of Maſter <hi>Fitzherbert.</hi> num. 206. pag. 69.</note>. Wherefore you muſt diſtinguiſh (as the aforeſayd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours doe well obſerue) betwixt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike verities and hereſies <hi>ſecundùm ſe, &amp; quoad nos,</hi> according to their owne nature, and in reſpect of vs; for hereſies without all condemnation of the Church are hereſies, although be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church hath declared them to bee hereſies, they are not alwayes knowne to all Catholikes, but to ſome more or leſſe, who ſee, that either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, or indirectly, they containe a falſhood repugnant to the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. See alſo the definition which S. <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Lincolne</hi> maketh of <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> related by <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> in the life of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the third. pag. 846.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 4. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>FOR though it be <hi>(ſay you)</hi> cleare in Scriptures,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> that none muſt doe wrong, yet it is not cleare in Scriptures,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:217:36"/>that the ſubiect, or other depoſing the Prince after depriuation, doth wrong. It is onely grounded on your rule, <hi>In pari caſu melior eſt conditio poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis, In the like caſe the condition of the poſſeſſor is the better;</hi> which, though it be true, and grounded on rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet it is not <hi>de fide, of faith,</hi> or ſet downe in Scripture, and conſequently the doing againſt it not hereticall. For (as you know) when a concluſion depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on two premiſſes, whereof the one is <hi>de fide, of faith,</hi> the other not, when according to the Logicians rule, <hi>The Concluſion muſt follow the weaker part,</hi> the concluſion cannot be <hi>de fide, of faith,</hi> and conſequently the contrary propoſition to that concluſion cannot bee hereticall. And ſo, though it be cleare in Scriptures, wee muſt doe no wrong, yet, becauſe it is not in Scriptures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that it is a wrong for the ſubiect, or other, to depoſe the Prince depriued, but proued ſo to bee by your rule, which is no Scripture, it can not be ſworne, that the doctrine ſo teaching is hereticall.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:217:36"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT this diſcourſe of yours is farre more weake,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient then the former. And <hi>firſt</hi> to ſhew the inſufficiency therof by ſome inconueniences; It is manifeſt, that, according to your principles, no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular propoſition is of faith, and the contrarie hereticall, although it bee neuer ſo cleerely contained in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall propoſition, which is expreſſed in the holy Scripture, vnleſſe both the premiſſes, to proue the particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to bee included in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, bee expreſſely contained in the holy Scripture. And ſo by your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of arguing, it is not lawfull to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure as <hi>hereticall,</hi> any particular do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which approueth the diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of particular Parents, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth any particular adultery, theft, or murther; although they bee neuer ſo vnqueſtionable diſhonouring, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable adultery, vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble theft, or murther. For to proue theſe particular and vnqueſtionable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:217:37"/>vnlawfull actions to bee included in thoſe generall precepts, <hi>Honour thy father and mother: Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery: Thou ſhalt not ſteale: Thou ſhalt not kill:</hi> one of the premiſſes is not contained in the holy Scripture, but it muſt be deduced from naturall reaſon, or humane teſtimonice, which are not Scriptures. For although it be cleare in Scriptures, that wee muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our father and mother, yet it is not ſet downe in Scriptures, although it be otherwiſe certaine, that this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man, or woman, is our father, or mother, but this muſt bee proued by humane teſtimonies, and naturall reaſon, which are not Scriptures. And although it bee cleare in Scriptures, that wee muſt not commit adulterie, yet it is not cleare in Scriptures, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee otherwiſe vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that this woman is another mans wife, and conſequently, that particular abuſe to be adultery, but this muſt bee proued out of Scriptures: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee cleare in Scriptures, that wee muſt not ſteale from any man his goods, yet it is not cleare in Scriptures,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:217:37"/>although it be otherwiſe certaine, that theſe goods are an other mans, but this muſt be proued out of Scripture. And although it be cleere in Scripture that we muſt not kill, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an vndoubted lawfull King, yet it is not cleare in Scripture, although it be otherwiſe certaine, either that this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular killing of a priuare man is don by priuate, and not by publike autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or that part cular man to bee a lawfull King, or a King, yea or to be a man, but theſe muſt bee proued by principles, which are no Scriptures. Many other examples may be brought out of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as of <hi>Prieſts</hi> to remit ſins, of <hi>Popes</hi> to be the chiefe Paſtors of the Church, of <hi>Sacraments</hi> to be effectuall outward ſignes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible grace, for that out of Scripture only we cannot proue any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer to bee a true <hi>Prieſt,</hi> any <hi>Pope</hi> whatſoeuer to bee a true <hi>Pope,</hi> or any <hi>Sacrament</hi> whatſoeuer to bee a true <hi>Sacrament,</hi> but to proue them to bee ſuch, one of the premiſſes muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the holy Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 But leaſt you ſhould obiect, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:217:38"/>
                     <hi>to draw one to an inconuenience is not to ſolue the argument, Secondly,</hi> I <hi>anſwere</hi> directly, that it is very vntrue in my iudgement, and alſo repugnant to the common doctrine of Diuines, that to make a Concluſion to bee faith, and the contrarie hereticall, both the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes muſt be expreſly and formally conteyned in the holy Scriptures, but it is ſufficient, that one onely of them bee expreſſed in the holy Scripture, and the other certaine by naturall reaſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ad fidem aliquîd pertinet duplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp;c. To faith a thing belongeth two waies</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Thomas</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 11. <hi>ar.</hi> 2.) <hi>one way directly and principally, as the Articles of faith: an other way indire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, and ſecondarily, as thoſe things, from which doth follow the corruption of ſome article.</hi> Which words of S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Bannes</hi> declareth more plainely &amp; diſtinctly in theſe words: <hi>Illa ſecundùm D. Thomam indirectè ſunt fidei &amp;c. Thoſe things, according to S.</hi> Thomas, <hi>are indirectly of faith, by the denying wherof, it followeth neceſſarily by a good conſequence that to be falſe, which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:217:38"/>firmed by faith. As if one deny</hi> Chriſt <hi>to haue power to laugh, doth erre in the Catholike faith conſequently, and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly. Becauſe it well followeth by a conſequence knowne by the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that</hi> Chriſt <hi>is not a perfect man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Et notandum est, aliquam propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem eſſe de fide duobus modis &amp;c. And it is to be noted</hi> (ſaith <hi>Franciſcus de Christo</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 23</note>) <hi>that a propoſition is of faith</hi> two <hi>waies,</hi> one <hi>way, proximè, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, of which ſort is euery propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which is formally and expreſly conteyned in the holy Scripture, as that</hi> Abraham <hi>had two ſonnes: the</hi> other way <hi>a propoſition is of faith mediatly, of which ſort is euery propoſition, which by a good conſequence is deduced from that which is immediately of faith, as that</hi> Chriſt <hi>had not power to vnderstand, &amp; that he had not a will &amp;c. Therefore that propoſition, which is deduced from that, which is formally conteyned in the holy Scriptures, is of faith, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition repugnant to that is hereticall.</hi> Thus he. And <hi>Franciſcus Pegna</hi> in his Annotations vpon the <hi>Directorie</hi> of the <hi>Inquiſitours</hi> part. 2. Comment.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:217:39"/>27. citing for the ſame <hi>Cardinal Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recremata,</hi> and other Doctours, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, or degree of <hi>Catholike verities,</hi> thoſe; <hi>which are by a neceſſarie conſequence deduced from the holy Scriptures.</hi> And a little after he affirmeth, <hi>that thoſe propoſitions are to be accounted hereticall, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to theſe Catholike aſſertions.</hi> And therefore I meruaile, that you ſhould conceiue that propoſition not to be heretical, which is deduced from <hi>two premiſſes,</hi> whereof the one is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly repugnant to the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the other deduced neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily from the light of naturall reaſon, or ſenſible experience, although wee ſhould take <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſenſe, wherein <hi>Widdrington</hi> doth take it. For according to your principles, M. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> could not maintaine, that it is hereticall to affirme, that <hi>Christ had not humane vnderstanding and will,</hi> and that, <hi>euery Tyrant may and ought lawfully &amp; meritoriouſly be ſlain by any whatſoeuer &amp;c.</hi> which neuertheleſſe are expreſly condemned by Generall Councels for hereticall; Becauſe to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:217:39"/>proue theſe propoſitions to be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, one of the premiſſes is only dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the light of naturall reaſon, which is no Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 And if perchance you ſhould anſwere, that theſe propoſitions are therefore hereticall, becauſe Generall Councels haue condemned them for heretical, now you fly from taking the word <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſenſe, wherein <hi>Widdrington</hi> with moſt Catholike Diuines, and all <hi>Protestants</hi> doe take the word <hi>hereticall,</hi> who hould that the definition, or declaration of the Church doth not make any Catholike veritie, or any doctrine hereticall, but ſuppoſe it, declare it, &amp; make it known to all Catholikes, which neuertheleſſe before any declaration, or definition of the Church, was indeed Catholike veritie, or hereticall doctrine, and alſo knowne ſo to be to diuerſe learned men, who euidently ſaw the neceſſarie conſequence from both the premiſſes. For alſo, as wel writeth <hi>Molina</hi> a moſt learned Ieſuite, <hi>Concurſus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Molina <hi>1.</hi> part. q. <hi>1.</hi> ar. <hi>2</hi> diſp. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>quo ſpiritus ſanctus praesto adest Eccleſiae &amp;c. The aſſistance, wherewith the holy Ghost is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:217:40"/>preſent with the Catholike Church, is not to make any thing of faith, which before was not of faith, but onely that ſhe do not erre in declaring thoſe things, which mediately, or immediately belong to faith. Wherefore, as in the Church there is not power &amp; authority to make any thing of faith, which before was not of faith, but only to declare to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, which is certainly to be held of faith, ſo alſo neither is there power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to make any ſacred Scripture, or to add to it any canonicall booke, or any part, but onely to iudge betwixt canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes, and not canonicall.</hi> Thus he, wherein, as you haue ſeene aboue<note n="i" place="margin">In the third <hi>Sectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note>, he agreeth with the common doctrine of Diuines.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Now to that Logicall maxime, <hi>That the Concluſion followeth the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker part,</hi> which is the chiefe ground of your obiection, I <hi>anſwer,</hi> that althogh it bee frequent in euerie mans mouth, yet you are not ignorant, that it is not by learned men vnderſtood, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded alike. And <hi>first,</hi> if you will vnderſtand it without exception, limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or declaration, how will you
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:217:40"/>make good <hi>Aristotles</hi> ſaying in his firſt booke of the <hi>Priors cap.</hi> 10. <hi>When the Maior propoſition is neceſſarie, and the Minor de ineſſe, the Concluſion is neceſſarie, and not de ineſſe,</hi> if the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion doe alwaies follow the weaker part?</p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>Secondly,</hi> you know, that many learned Diuines, whom <hi>Molina</hi> the Ieſuite in the place aboue cited doth follow, expound it thus, That the Concluſion followeth the weaker part <hi>quoad certitudinem &amp; euidentiam,</hi> in reſpect of certitude and euidence, <hi>wherein the Concluſion dependeth vpon both the premiſſes, non quoad ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalitatem,</hi> not in regard of ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalitie, <hi>wherein it only dependeth vpon Diuine</hi> and ſupernaturall <hi>faith.</hi> For to make an act <hi>ſupernaturall,</hi> it is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, that one of the cauſes be <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall,</hi> as it is apparant in the acts of contrition, of faith, hope, and charity, to which concurre the vnderſtanding. and will of man, which are naturall cauſes, and yet they are <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> acts, becauſe they are produced by a <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> habite, for which cauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:217:41"/>they affirme, that a <hi>Theological conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> deduced from one principle of faith, and from the other knowne by the light of naturall reaſon, is <hi>ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,</hi> becauſe it is produced by the <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> habite of faith.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> others (who hould with S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and the common doctrine of Diuines, that doctrine to be of faith which either directly and expreſly, or indirectly, and vertually is conteyned in the holy Scripture, and the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be hereticall, &amp; that the Church doth not make Catholike veritie or hereſie, but onely doth declare, and make it certainely knowne to all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, which before her declaration was not certainly knowne to all) doe anſwere thus: That the Concluſion followeth the weaker part, <hi>principally, directly,</hi> and <hi>immediately:</hi> but when the weaker part is neceſſarily conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſtronger, then alſo the Concluſion doth follow the ſtronger part, <hi>ſecundarily, indirectly,</hi> and <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</hi> And the reaſon hereof is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; for when one thing is neceſſarily connected with an other, that which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:217:41"/>followeth the one, muſt conſequently follow the other, at the leaſt ſecunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, indirectly, and mediately. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſeeing that all diſhonouring of Parents, all Theft, all Murder, all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie are againſt Scripture directly and expreſly, it neceſſarily followeth, that euerie particular contained in the generall, being ſufficiently proued to be conteyned therein, (of whatſoeuer kind that proofe be) is alſo indirectly, vertually, or by a neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence repugnant to Scripture. And hereby alſo appeareth the weakeneſſe of the application you make of your argument to the <hi>murthering</hi> of Princes which are excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, in theſe words following.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 5. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>IN like manner <hi>(ſay you)</hi> though it be cleare in Scriptures,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> we must not murther, yet it is not cleare in Scripture, that it is murther, if a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate man go about to kill a Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, if he ſtill vſurpe, when Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:217:42"/>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers may be ſlayne by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, as all doe grant. I ſay, if he ſtill vſurpe; for if he do not, but yeeld vp his Crowne, as ſome haue done after depriuation, it were euident murther to kill ſuch a Prince, as all doe teach. It is onely deduced out of your rule, <hi>In pari caſu &amp;c. In the like caſe &amp;c.</hi> to be murther; which rule when it is not in Scripture, as I ſaid before, the oppoſite doctrine can not bee he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt <hi>first,</hi> although it be not cleare in Scriptures directly and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that it is <hi>murther</hi> to kill a <hi>Prince</hi> excommunicated or depriued by the <hi>Pope,</hi> if he will not obey his ſentence of depriuation (not to vſe your vnreſpectiue words, <hi>if hee ſtill vſurpe,</hi> ſeeing that a Prince, who hath poſſeſſion, and a probable title, is by none accounted an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi>) yet it is repugnant to Scriptures indirectly, vertually, and by a neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to kill ſuch a Prince: for that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:217:42"/>neither Excommunication, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth him onely of ſpirituall graces, nor depriuation, which depriueth him onely of his kingdome (according to thoſe that hould it for certain that the Pope hath authoritie to depriue Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) &amp; not of his life, can hinder, that the killing of ſuch a Prince is not included in that generall, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> I wonder that you houlding it probable (as I ſuppoſe) that the Pope hath not authoritie to depriue Princes, ſhould ſo dangerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; ſeditiouſly apply that ſimilitude of killing <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> to the killing of Princes excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, ſeeing that the doctrine of killing <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> is vnderſtood by all that approue it, of known, manifeſt and vndoubted <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and not of ſuch, as haue poſſeſſion, &amp; alſo a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable title to the Crowne, as haue all thoſe Princes, which are excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated or depriued by the Pope, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be a controuerſie among Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes (as vndoubtedly it is) whether the Pope hath authoritie to depriue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:217:43"/>wicked Princes, or no.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>if</hi> 3 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that which you ſay <hi>[that he yeeld vp his Crowne as ſome haue done, it were euident murther in any one to go about to kill ſuch a Prince]</hi> is very true, yet it is not cleare and expreſly contained in Scripture, but to proue it euident murther, you muſt vſe the helpe of an argument, whereof one of the premiſſes is not formally and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely contained in Scripture. And therefore, according to your grounds, you could not abiure as <hi>hereticall</hi> that doctrine, which ſhould maintaine it for no murther, although you grant it to be euident murther.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> if you will call to mind the Hiſtories of thoſe Princes, who haue yeelded vp their Crownes after depriuation, whereof you can name but very few, you ſhall find ſuch ſtuffe about the practiſe of this doctrine of depoſing, that any zealous Catholike may bee aſhamed thereof. Among thoſe few Princes, remember our king <hi>Iohn,</hi> who rendred vp his Crown after depriuation. But to whom did hee yeeld or render it? Not to the next
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:217:43"/>heire of the blood Royall, who after King <hi>Iohns</hi> depriuation was <hi>forthwith</hi> the true King by <hi>right,</hi> if King <hi>Iohn</hi> was truly and really depriued, but hee gaue it to the <hi>Pope.</hi> And how, I pray you, could hee giue that to the Pope, whereof hee was depriued, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently had no right therein, if the <hi>Pope</hi> had truly authoritie to depriue him? Or how could the <hi>Pope</hi> accept thereof, if King <hi>Iohn</hi> when he gaue it to the Pope was depriued thereof, and conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly had no right to giue that which was not his. But let vs on to the reſt of your Diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 6. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>ANd as for the examples you produce to proue <hi>(ſay you)</hi> that theſe particulars are conteyned in the generals,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> me thinke they are not ſo good and apt for that purpoſe, and in them I find a great diſparitie. For to take a purſe from our neighbour, or to kill him with a penne knife, if hee lead a wanton life, are vnqueſtionable theft, and murther, and included in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:217:44"/>the generals; and that one liueth a wicked life can no way bee excuſe for the fault committed: But to depoſe or kill a Prince depriued, if after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation hee vſurpe, is with many queſtionable, and probably thought by ſome neither theft nor murther: and ſo though to you, according to your rule, they may be thought ſo to be, yet by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they are no more reputed ſuch, or included in the generall propoſition of theft and murther, then taking a Cow or Horſe from the enemie in time of warre, when the cauſe is iuſt, or kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Tyrant in call Vſurper in a Common-Wealth, which neither are Theft nor Murther, nor can with ſafe conſcience be ſworne ſo to be.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt <hi>first,</hi> you greatly abuſe the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres gift,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> in affirming, that he brought thoſe examples to make a paritie or ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude betwixt them, and the depoſing and murthering of Princes excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated or depriued by the Pope.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:217:44"/>For hee brought them onely to ſhew, that it is not neceſſarie to make a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <hi>de fide, of faith,</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie <hi>heretical,</hi> that it be formally, and expreſly contained in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but that it ſuffiſeth to be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vertually, &amp; by a neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and that no word, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance expreſſed in the particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition doe hinder, that it be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the generall propoſition, which is formally and expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the holy Scripture. Neither did he apply them otherwiſe, as you may ſee, if you will pervſe the place.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> although he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared them together, as hee did not, yet the paritie is not ſo vnapt, as you would ſeeme to make it. For albeit there be a great diſparity betwixt them (as there is betwixt ſalt and ſugar in taſt but not in colour) yet they both agree in this, for which onely purpoſe he brought thoſe examples, that they are not formally and expreſly contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the holy Scriptures, but onely by a neceſſarie conſequence proued to be Theft and Murther; as alſo the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:217:45"/>depoſing and murthering of Princes excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, are by a neceſſarie conſequence proued by the ſaid <hi>Authour</hi> to bee Theft and Murther, and conſequently comprehended in thoſe generall words, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale, Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> as particulars in the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>But to take a purſe from his neighbour, or to kill him with a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll, if hee leade a wicked life, are vnqueſtionable Theft and Murther</hi> (ſay you) <hi>and included in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals &amp;c.</hi> This is verie true, and for that cauſe the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres Gift</hi> brought thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. But you can not proue by Scriptures onely, that they are vnqueſtionable Theft and Murther, becauſe they are not formally and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden in the word of God, but to proue them to be vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Theft and Murther, you muſt vſe a Syllogiſme, whereof one of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes is not in the Word of God, but grounded on the light of naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is no Scripture. And ſo,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:217:45"/>according to the Diſcourſe you made aboue, although this Theft, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee vndoubtedly contained in thoſe generalls, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale, Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> yet you cannot ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure, as <hi>hereticall,</hi> that doctrine, which approueth them to bee lawfull. Nay, according to your grounds, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abiure <hi>as hereticall</hi> that doctrine, which holdeth it lawfull to kill any particular man whatſoeuer, although it be moſt aſſuredly Murther, for that you cannot proue by Scriptures, that hee is a man, but this premiſſe you muſt proue by naturall reaſon, or eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſence, neither of which is Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>But to depoſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>or kill a Prince depriued, if after depriuation hee vſurpe, is with many queſtionable, and probably thought by ſome, neither Theft, nor Murther,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To kill a Prince depriued by the Pope is by no man queſtionable,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Suarez</hi> in Defenſ. fidei Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. &amp;c. lib. 6. ca. 4. num. 10.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Pope, after depriuation, giue a particular commiſſion to kill him. And in this caſe onely <hi>Suarez</hi> among all that euer I read, durſt aduenture
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:217:46"/>to teach expreſſely, <hi>That if the Pope giue ſuch a commiſſion to any priuate man, hee may lawfully kill ſuch a Prince.</hi> But conſidering that this ſeditious, or rather diabolicall doctrine is, grounded vpon a moſt falſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable foundation, to wit, that it is a cleare poynt of faith, and out of all controuerſie among Catholikes, that the Pope hath authority to diſpoſe of the Crownes, and alſo liues of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Princes in order to ſpiritual good, which all the world ſeeth not onely to bee a controuerſie among them, but alſo to bee condemned by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> for a <hi>falſe and ſeditious, damnable and pernicious doctrine,</hi> it is manifeſt, that the concluſion, which is grounded vpon this falſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable foundation, cannot bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. And therefore thoſe your words <hi>[and probably thought by ſome, to be neither Theft, nor Murther]</hi> are very vntrue, and dangerous, and alſo the examples you bring in <hi>taking ſpoyles from the enemy in time of iuſt war,</hi> and <hi>killing a Tyrant in call an Vſurper,</hi> are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptly and perniciouſly (not to ſay ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiouſly,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:217:46"/>applyed by you to the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a Prince depriued by the Pope, or taking from him his Crown: both for that depriuation doth not take away the right hee hath to liue, neither is that Prince, keeping his Crowne after depriuation, ſuch a knowne and manifeſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper,</hi> as that he hath not at leaſt a probable title to the Crowne, of which manifeſt <hi>Vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> only, thoſe Diuines, who approue the killing of <hi>Vſurpers,</hi> doe ſpeake. And that it is manifeſt <hi>Theft,</hi> to take from a Prince his Crown, to which he hath a probable right after depriuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you ſhal ſee more plainly beneath.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 7. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>BEſides your expoſition <hi>(ſay you)</hi> of thoſe words [<hi>depoſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                     <hi>or murther</hi>] taken out of <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his <hi>Theologicall Diſputation,</hi> to proue the lawfulnes of ſwearing this Branch, ſeemeth to me not altogether ſo ſound. For though indeed ſuch examples may be found ſometimes, yea and oftentimes (as he well doth demonſtrate) wherein for the truth of a conditionall diſiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:217:47"/>propoſition, it ſufficeth, that the one part be true, though the other bee falſe, and conſequently wee may ſweare the whole propoſition, if the one part bee but true, yet <hi>hic &amp; nunc</hi> in this Oath, and with theſe circumſtances, with the words going before, and the words com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after, adding therunto the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law-maker, who no doubt would haue vs no leſſe deteſt the one, then the other, it cannot bee, but they muſt by the Oath bee both abiured as <hi>hereticall;</hi> and conſequently, this eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the conditionall diſiunctiue can helpe nothing here to ſaue from periury.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT <hi>firſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> you are greatly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in ſetting downe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> doctrine concerning the nature of a conditionall diſiunctiue propoſition. For he doth not ſay, that to the truth, but to the falſhood of a conditionall diſiunctiue propoſition it ſufficeth, that the one part bee true, though the other befalſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that wee may, hee doth ſay,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:217:47"/>ſweare, but abiure the whole propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the one part bee but true. But this your miſtaking I do not attribute to any want of you in the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> doctrine in this point, but onely to the errour and haſtineſſe of your pen.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he doth not onely ſay, that <hi>ſometimes and oftentimes,</hi> but alſo that <hi>moſt commonly</hi> the conditionall diſiunctiue propoſition, to wit, when the Coniunction <hi>[or]</hi> followeth the Verbe <hi>[may]</hi> is ſo to be taken; and that there can ſcarſe bee alledged any one conditionall diſiunctiue propoſition, wherein it is not ſo to bee taken: and that therefore, according to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Branch,</hi> we ought to take it ſo in this Clauſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I maruell, that you ſhould ſo reſolutely affirme, without alledging any reaſon, that <hi>without doubt the intention of the Law-maker is, that wee ſhould no leſſe deteſt the one part of the propoſition, then the other;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſeeing that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath anſwered at large this obiection in his Confutation of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> who
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:217:48"/>vrged the ſame obiection more fully, then you haue done, and yet you vrge here M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzherberts</hi> obiection, and take no notice of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſame. And is it poſſible, that a man of your learning can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> doth deteſt no leſſe (that is in the ſame degree of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation and falſity) the doctrine of <hi>murthering</hi> Princes excommunicated, or depriued of the Pope, then he doth of <hi>depoſing</hi> them? Or, that he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that the doctrine of <hi>murthering</hi> the ſaid Princes, is not more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly falſe, and againſt Scripture, then is the doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> them? If you had diligently peruſed his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> bookes, you might haue ſeene, that againſt the doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> Princes by the Popes authority, hee bringeth many proofes, both out of the <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new Teſtament,</hi> but againſt the doctrine of <hi>murthering</hi> them, hee doth not ſo much labour; for that he ſuppoſeth it to bee ſo manifeſtly falſe, that no Catholike, or Chriſtian Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine could bee ſo temetarious, as to approue the ſame.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:217:48"/>
                  <p n="4">4. But howſoeuer his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> bee perſwaded, yet his intention (which in this Oath wee muſt chiefly regard, and not his beleefe, perſwaſion, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion) is (for as much as by reaſon, and his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> declaration wee can coniecture) that wee ſhould take the words, according to the common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of them, as wee are expreſſely bound by the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Branch</hi> of the Oath, which, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath proued, is, that we are not bound to abiure both parts for <hi>hereticall.</hi> And truely I wonder, that whereas you may, and are bound to expound the words in a fauourable ſenſe, you ſeeke all euaſions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, to expound them in a ſenſe moſt falſe and abſurd, to the ouerthrowing of the temporall eſtates of Engliſh Catholikes, to the diſgrace of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty,</hi> and to the ſcandall of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Roman</hi> Religion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 8. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>MOreouer,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> the ground <hi>(ſay you)</hi> whereon the lawfulneſſe of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:217:49"/>that the doctrin, which maintaineth the Popes authority to depoſe Princes after depriuation is hereticall, is not ſo certaine. For it is this ſole rule, <hi>In du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio melior eſt conditio poſſidentis, In a doubt the condition of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor is the better:</hi> which rule ſeemeth to mee to be vnderſtood rather <hi>in vero dubio,</hi> in a true doubt, and when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide hath probability, as when the minde doth fluctuate betwixt two, and can yeeld aſſent to neither part of the contradiction, then otherwiſe; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Popes power to depoſe Princes there is no ſuch doubt, or fluctuation, but both parts by you are thought pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, at the leaſt ſpeculatiuely.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT <hi>firſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> albeit this rule bee oftentimes cited by Doctors, <hi>In cauſa dubia,</hi> or <hi>In dubio</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In a doubtfull cauſe,</hi> or <hi>In a doubt,</hi> &amp;c. yet both the <hi>Canon</hi> and <hi>Ciuill Law,</hi> and you your ſelfe aboue doe cite it, <hi>In paricaſu,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In the like caſe,</hi> &amp;c. And why doe not you now cite it in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:217:49"/>ſame manner as you did aboue. <hi>In the like caſe</hi> &amp;c. but, <hi>In a doubt.</hi> Is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that you can imagine, that when both ſides haue probability, <hi>non eſt par caſus, The caſe is not alike?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> not onely this rule, <hi>In pari caſu</hi> &amp;c. <hi>In the like caſe</hi> &amp;c. But alſo (beſides that other rule, <hi>Cum ſunt inra partium</hi> &amp;c. <hi>When the rights of the parties, who are in ſtrife, are obſcure,</hi> or not cleare; <hi>the Defendant is rather to be fauoured, then the Plaintiffe,</hi>) The common doctrine of Diuines, wherof ſome are cited in the <hi>New-yeares Gift</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">In the <hi>firſt</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. nu. 11. pag. 43.</note>, who vnderſtand it not onely of a true, but alſo of a probable doubt, and who alſo in my iudgement proue the ſame by conuincing reaſons: And yet you bring no other reaſon, or authoritie, that it is to be vnderſtood onely of a <hi>true doubt,</hi> but your owne conceipt [<hi>which rule ſeemeth to me</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to be vnderſtood rather in a true doubt, and when neither ſide hath probabilitie, then otherwiſe</hi>] Is this (thinke you) a ſound and ſincere confutation of <hi>Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> doctrine in a matter, which is ſo iniurious to the ſoueraigne right of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:217:50"/>Princes, and ſo preiudiciall and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the ſoules and temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Engliſh Catholikes?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 9. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>AND although <hi>Leſſius</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with you ſeeme to hold <hi>(ſay you)</hi> that none can bee depriued of his right vpon a probable title onely,<note place="margin">Obiect</note> yet that muſt be vnderſtood firſt, if that right bee not retained with the wrong of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or the retaining of that right bee not the hinderance of a greater good.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT <hi>firſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> why do you vſe thoſe words <hi>[ſeem to hold]</hi> as though they did not in very deed hold, that none can bee depriued of his right to that, whereof hee hath poſſeſſion, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a probable power, or title onely, whereas it is manifeſt, that they doe expreſſely hold the ſame?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> why did you omit thoſe words <hi>[vpon a probable power]</hi> whereas there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:217:50"/>a <hi>probable power</hi> to <hi>puniſh,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> and a <hi>probable title,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leſſius</hi> in his <hi>Single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> part. 2. num. 38.</note> and <hi>Leſſius</hi> ſpeaketh expreſſely of a <hi>probable power</hi> to <hi>puniſh,</hi> and to <hi>depriue</hi> one of that; which he actually poſſeſſeth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly, Leſſius</hi> proueth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of a probable power to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh by a conuincing argument: <hi>For if it were any way doubtfull, the perſon accuſed might except againſt the Iudge, and not obey him. And hereupon credit is not giuen to delegates, to the preiudice of another man vnleſſe by an authenticall Inſtrument they ſhew their authoritie, ſo that no iuſt cauſe of doubt be further left:</hi> And D. <hi>Kellinſon</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">In his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> called, <hi>The Prince, and the Prelate,</hi> cap. 11. pa. 235.</note> with others proue the inſufficiency of a probable title, without poſſeſſion by thoſe two rules aboue cited, <hi>In pari caſu,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Cum ſunt iura partium obſcura,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Vaſquez</hi> confirmeth the ſame, as you ſhall ſee beneath,<note n="l" place="margin">Sect. 10. num. 2.</note> by other reaſons in his iudgement vnanſwerable. And yet you, without bringing any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, reaſon, or proofe at all, affirme too too reſolutely [<hi>that it muſt bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood firſt, if that right be not retained with the wrong of others,</hi> by whom you
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:217:51"/>meane the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Church</hi>] whereas they vnderſtand it generally, and alſo the former <hi>Authors</hi> ſpeake expreſſely of the Popes power to depoſe wicked Princes: where you falſly ſuppoſe a wrong done to the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> in reſiſting the Popes ſentence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation: For a Prince, being depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued onely by a probable power, doth no man wrong by keeping his proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right and poſſeſſion, according to that <hi>maxime</hi> of the Law, grounded on naturall reaſon, <hi>Qui vtitur iure ſuo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini facit iniuriam: Hee that vſeth his right doth no man wrong.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Moreouer, your firſt exception <hi>[if that right bee not retained with the wrong of others]</hi> is friuolous, for that alwaies in the caſe of rights to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Kingdomes and goods, it may be preſumed, that the right is retained with the wrong, or rather detriment of others, becauſe temporall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and goods, if they doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Prince, or perſon depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they muſt needes belong to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And <hi>beſides,</hi> as it hath been ſaid aboue, a probableright with poſſeſſion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:217:51"/>is retained without wrong to any man. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> your <hi>ſecond</hi> excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>[or if the retaining of that right bee not a hinderance to a greater good]</hi> doth ſauour too much of that falſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ouer much frequent in the mouths and actions of ſome vnlearned Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, <hi>Ad maiorem gloriam Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>To the greater glory of God,</hi> &amp;c. For good ends, and greater good are not to bee effected by bad meanes: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, albeit the retaining of that right ſhould bee an hinderance to a greater good, it little importeth, vnleſſe it be an <hi>vniuſt</hi> hinderance, and vnleſſe the Prince depriued by a probable power onely, in keeping his probable right with poſſeſſion, hindereth <hi>vniuſtly</hi> a greater good: which to bee an <hi>vniuſt</hi> hinderance, you cannot poſſibly proue with any colour of a probable argument, as more plainely you ſhall ſee beneath.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 10. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>AND ſecondly <hi>(ſay you)</hi> if they who contend about that right,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:217:52"/>haue a Superiour to decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, and determine vnto whom the right belongeth: But if one, by retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that right vpon a probable title, ſhould wrong others, whoſe good is more to bee reſpected, then his, who is in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that right; or if thoſe, who contend about right, haue no Superiour to decide the matter, and to determine to whom the right belongeth, I ſee not, why one may not bee depriued of his right vpon a probable title. And ſo we ſee, that Kings and Princes, who haue no Superiours, but euery one is ſupreme Lord in his owne dominions, oftentimes fall to wars, and one ſeeke to diſpoſſeſſe another onely vpon a probable title.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVT <hi>firſt</hi> it is manifeſt, that no man,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> who hath a probable right, and withall poſſeſſion, doth any wrong to another, of what qualitie, condition, or ſtate ſoeuer hee bee, by keeping his probable right and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and that no good is to bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by vniuſt meanes, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:217:52"/>that the retaining of a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right with poſſeſſion cannot be an <hi>vniuſt hinderance</hi> to the good of any, whether it bee the <hi>Pope,</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> it ſelfe. For if to inuade the Kingdome of a <hi>Prince,</hi> onely vpon a probable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle without poſſeſſion, bee no wrong, or any <hi>vniuſt</hi> hinderance of a greater good (as you, in <hi>Vaſquez</hi> iudgement, very <hi>falſly, perniciouſly,</hi> and <hi>abſurdly</hi> ſuppoſe) much more it is no wrong, nor any <hi>iuſt hinderance</hi> to greater good, for a <hi>Prince</hi> to defend his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to which hee hath not onely a probable right, but alſo poſſeſſion thereof. And therfore that exception of yours <hi>[But if one by retaining his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable right, ſhould wrong others, whoſe good is more to be reſpected, then his, who is in poſſeſſion of that right]</hi> is idle, and cannot bee applyed to a <hi>Prince,</hi> who iuſtly retaineth his probable right, to the Kingdome whereof hee hath poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and conſequently without any wrong to others, whoſe good muſt not be reſpected, or effected by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrong to him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> albeit <hi>you do not ſee why
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:217:53"/>one may not be depriued of his right vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a probable title, if thoſe who contend for right haue no Superior to decide the matter, and to determine to whom the right belongeth,</hi> yet you might eaſily haue ſeene a reaſon thereof, if you had called to mind the doctrine of your Maiſter <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez,</hi> who ſaw and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a reaſon thereof ſo clearely,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vaſques</hi> 1.2 <hi>diſp</hi> 64. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> that hee feared not to taxe this your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine not onely of falſhood, but alſo of pernitious improbabilitie, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie. <hi>Immo ſemper exiſtimaui hanc doctrinam nihil probabilitis habere &amp;c. Yea I haue euer thought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this doctrine to haue no probabilitie, and to haue bin in no little miſchief, and detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Chriſtian Common-wealth.</hi> And therefore hee would not haue ſticked to deteſt your doctrin, as <hi>falſe, improbable, pernitious,</hi> and the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to acknowledge for <hi>certaine:</hi> and he proueth it by theſe reaſons, which, in his iudgement, are conuincing: <hi>For warre is an act of punitiue Iustice, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting a puniſhment, and chaſtiſing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels: and the nature of iust warre conſisteth in this, that by vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:217:53"/>iuſtice hee bee puniſhed, who is worthy of puniſhment in regard of ſome fault, either actually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or at leaſt wiſe iuſtly preſumed.</hi> But it cannot be <hi>iustly preſumed,</hi> that a Prince committeth any fault, who, by way of defence, retaineth his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hable right to the kingdome which he poſſeſſeth, againſt the pretenſions of any one, who claimeth onely a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right without poſſeſſion. <hi>Et praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea omnis controuerſia &amp;c. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer euerie controuerſie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which is in opinions concerning ſome right, is not to bee decided by powerfulneſſe and armes, but by iudgment. For it ſeemeth to bee the custome of Barbarous men to decide the better right to reigne in the more powerfull armes.</hi> Quod ſi dicas, poſſe duos illos Principes &amp;c. <hi>And if thou ſay</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſques</hi>) <hi>that thoſe two Princes may make iust warre on either ſide, for that both of them are led by a probable opinion, and thinke that the right to reigne belongeth to them, this is manifestly abſurd &amp;c.</hi> which he doth there, in his iudgement, moſt plainely conuince. Neuertheleſſe, as you ſhall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:217:54"/>ſee beneath<note n="m" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. nu. 2.</note> I rely vpon a more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; leſſe queſtionable ground, then this doctrine of <hi>Vaſques;</hi> for this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion concerning Princes making warre vpon a probable title, which is meerely temporall, I will ſhew to be impertinent to our preſent controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, concerning the Popes authority to depoſe Princes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> albeit ſome few Diuines doe hould (which <hi>Vaſquez</hi> accounteth to be manifeſtly abſurd and improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) that it is lawfull for Princes to make warre vpon a probable title, yet ſome of them expreſly affirme, that thoſe Princes, who contend about their probable title, are bound, before they can lawfully make war,<note place="margin">Nouar in Sion. cap. <hi>25</hi> nu. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> to chuſe and admit Arbitrary Iudges to decide the controuerſie, for that there is no other peaceable way (they being both ſupreme Iudges, nor the one ſubiect to the other, or to any other ſuperiour Iudge in temporals) to end it but by arbitrement: which if any of thoſe Princes refuſe to admit, then the other Prince (ſay theſe Diuines) may make warre, but not in regard onely of his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:217:54"/>probable title, but for doing wrong in not admitting Arbiters, to end the controuerſie in a peaceable manner, without making warre, for that warre muſt not be waged, when the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie may otherwiſe bee peaceably ended. But neither alſo with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie will I intermeddle.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> whereas you ſay <hi>[that Kings and Princes, who haue no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours oftentimes fall to warres, and one ſeeke to diſpoſſeſſe an other onely vpon a probable title]</hi> you might for anſwere hereof haue called to minde, what <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> related by <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">In his <hi>Apologie</hi> for the right of Princes, <hi>nu.</hi> 445</note>, anſwereth to ſuch kind of arguments, <hi>Aliud est facta Regum referre &amp;c. It is one thing to relate the facts of Kings, and an other to proue their power &amp; authoritie.</hi> And beſides it may verie well be, that the Prince, who beginneth the warre, thinketh his title to be certaine, and the others title not to bee probable. And moreouer the title, for which they make warre, may be meerely temporall, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not to our caſe, as you ſhall ſee beneath. But let vs go on to the reſt of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:217:55"/>your obiections.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 11. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>ANd if a probable title <hi>(ſay you)</hi> were not ſufficient excuſe for the diſpoſſeſſing of the right,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> which an other houldeth, it were as good haue no title at all, as a probable title with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſeſſion.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt <hi>first,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> your conſequence is not good. For no title is good for nothing, but a probable title with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſeſſion, in ſubiects is good for this, to call the title in queſtion, and to haue it examined &amp; decided by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vndoubted Iudge: and in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Princes, who haue no Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in temporals, it is good in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſome Diuines to haue the matter put to arbitrement or compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which if the Prince, who is in poſſeſſion refuſe, the other Prince may (according to the doctrine of theſe Diuines, wherewith I will not meddle)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:217:55"/>make warre againſt him, for the wrong done him in not admitting Arbiters. Alſo a probable title without poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is better then no title, for that it is good after the deceaſe of them who haue poſſeſſion, to haue the matter decided by the Kingdome or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to whom it belongeth (as well obſerueth <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi>) to determin doubtfull titles, when none is in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: As alſo, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of all Diuines, it belongeth to the Church, or Spirituall kingdome of Chriſt (which a general Councel doth repreſent) to determine and decide the doubtfull titles of two Popes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though both of them be partly in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> your conſequent, for as much as concerneth the making of warre vpon a probable title without poſſeſſion, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi> would not feare to admit. For it is not abſurd to graunt, that a probable title without poſſeſſion is as good as no title, for the making of warre againſt a Prince, who hath both a probable title and alſo poſſeſſion. As alſo it is no abſurditie
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:217:56"/>to grant, but rather a moſt certaine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that aprobable matter of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is in ſome caſe, for as much as concerneth practiſe, as good as no matter,<note place="margin">See <hi>Vaſques</hi> 1.2 <hi>diſp.</hi> 63 <hi>&amp; diſp.</hi> 64 <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</note> for that it is not lawful in ſome caſe to baptize with a probable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to wit, when we may vſe a certaine and vndoubted matter: And a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable medicine is in ſome caſe as good as no medicine, for that it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to apply to one a probable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, when an vndoubted medicine may be applyed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 12. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>NOw in this contention <hi>(ſay you)</hi> betwixt the pope,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> &amp; the Prince, though the Prince haue a probable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after depriuation, and alſo poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is houlden with wrong to the Church, &amp; preiudice to Chriſts flocke, whoſe good is more to bee reſpected, then the priuate good of a temporall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prince. And ſo it ſeemeth, he may be depriued of his right vpon a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title (though abſolutely abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:217:56"/>from ſuch caſe it may not bee done)</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt this hath beene fully anſwered aboue:<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> For it is a moſt falſe and ſeditious doctrine to hould, that a Prince in keeping the poſſeſſion of his Crown, to which (as you confeſſe) he hath a probable right after depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doth any wrong, or iniurie to the Church, or any <hi>vniust</hi> preiudice to Chriſts flocke, or that the good of the Church, or of Chriſts flocke is to bee reſpected, or obtained by <hi>vniust</hi> meanes, and with the wrong of any man, much leſſe of Princes, who in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; defending their probable right being in poſſeſſion, do no man wrong: For if it be no wrong (as you, in <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez</hi> iudgement, falſly and abſurdly ſuppoſe) for the Pope or Prince, who hath onely a probable title without poſſeſſion, to inuade and aſſault an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince, who hath both a probable title, and alſo poſſeſſion, much more it is no wrong for this Prince ſo aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:217:57"/>to defend himſelfe. And therefore you muſt not bee ſo mindfull of the good of the Church, or other good ends, that you forget, that the good of the Church, and all good ends muſt be obtained by good meanes, for as you know, <hi>Bonum est ex integra cauſa &amp;c. Good proceedeth from and entier cauſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dioniſius Areo pag. <hi>4.</hi> cap. de diu. nom.</note> 
                     <hi>but euill from euerie defect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> I doe not well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that exception you make in your laſt words <hi>[though abſolutely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from ſuch caſe it may not bee done]</hi> For I do not ſee, but that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the principles of your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, if an hereticall or wicked Prince bee depriued by the Pope, his Kingdome muſt alwaies bee held by him with wrong to the Church, and preiudice to Chriſts flocke &amp;c. and ſo that exception of yours, whereby you would ſeeme to limit your former falſe aſſertion, is in my conceipt to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe. And <hi>moreouer,</hi> whether it better for Gods glorie, and the good of the Church,<note place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>1.</hi> de SS. Petro &amp; Paulo</note> to haue ſomtimes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, <hi>Whereby</hi> (as S. <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith) <hi>the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:217:57"/>Church is not diminiſhed, but increaſed &amp;c.</hi> We cannot ſo eaſily know, and therefore wee ought rather to leaue it to the iudgement of him, <hi>who maketh a man that is an hypocrite reigne for the ſinnes of the people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 34.</note> then ouer raſhly to iudge of the ſecrets of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 13. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>AGaine, though in your conceipt and opinion</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the Pope and Prince haue a Superiour or head to iudge the controuerſie betwixt them,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> to wit, a generall Councell, yet in the opinion of others, who hould, that the Pope is aboue the Councell, and conſequently hath no head, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Pope may (as other Princes may without iniurie) goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Prince depriued vpon a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble title, though in full poſſeſſion of his right and dominions.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:217:58"/>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 MY conceit indeed is, that it is very probable that a generall Councel excluding the Pope is aboue atrue and vndoubted Pope,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> and that to conceiue the contrarie is altogether improbable and abſurd. Now to your argument: <hi>First</hi> therefore I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aboue, that according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez</hi> (which he thinketh to be <hi>certaine,</hi> and the contrarie <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, abſurd,</hi> and <hi>pernitious</hi>) no Prince can lawfully in regard only of the probabilitie of his title, make warre againſt an other Prince, who, beſides a probable title, hath alſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 But <hi>ſecondly</hi> (becauſe I will not meddle with this queſtion concerning Princes making warre vpon probable titles, which are meerely temporal, for that it is impertinent to our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie concerning the Popes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to depoſe princes) you may obſerue a great diſparitie betwixt the titles or rights, which temporall Princes doe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:217:58"/>commonly pretend to the kingdomes which other Princes poſſeſſe, and the right or title, which any Prince can pretend, by vertue of the Popes ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of depriuation to the kingdom of an other Prince. For the <hi>first</hi> titles or rights are for the moſt part <hi>meerely temporall titles,</hi> nor grounded vpon any <hi>ſpirituall authoritie,</hi> and therefore they are not ſubiect to the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> or to the deciſion of the Spirituall authoritie of the Church, which, by the inſtitution of Chriſt, hath infallible aſſiſtance to determine and decide <hi>only Spirituall,</hi> and not <hi>meere temporall cauſes:</hi> But the <hi>ſecond</hi> right is grounded vpon the Popes pretended authority to depriue Princes of their temporall rights, which authoritie (if there be any ſuch as I am fully perſwaded there is not) it being a Spiritual matter, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding chiefly vpon the inſtitution of Chriſt, deliuered to vs in the Word of God, is to be decided, when it is called in queſtion among learned Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, by Spirituall and not temporall authority, and therefore it is ſubiect to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:217:59"/>the determination and deciſion of a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> which, without all controuerſie among Catholikes, is an infallible meanes, to know certainly, what authoritie <hi>Christ</hi> hath giuen to the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 And if you had duly obſerued this diſparitie betwixt temporall and ſpirituall titles, you might eaſily haue perceiued the weakeneſſe of your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection. For it is too too manifeſt, that all <hi>Princes</hi> are bound to ſearch out, by all poſſible &amp; conuenient meanes, the truth, or falſhood of the rights, which they with probabilitie pretend to the Kingdome, which an other <hi>Prince</hi> poſſeſſeth with a probable title before they can iuſtly make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, in regard onely of their probable title; and if there be any aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and peaceable way to finde out the truth, they are bound to try the ſame, before they can, by warre or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, diſpoſſeſs any <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath a probable title to his Crown: becauſe according to the doctrine of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, no <hi>Prince</hi> can lawfully make warre (wherein the blood of ſo many
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:217:59"/>innocent men is by all probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectures likely to be ſhed) to try an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine title, if the certainty of his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, may be cleerely knowne and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by any other aſſured &amp; vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted peaceable way. Seeing therefore, that <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his <hi>Church</hi> an aſſured and infallible way, and which all Catholikes acknowledge to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, to finde out the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie concerning the titles, which are grounded vpon the Popes pretended authoritie to depriue Princes, to wit, the determination and deciſion of a lawfull and vndoubted <hi>generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> it is euident, that both the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Catholike Princes,</hi> are bound by this infallible and peaceable way to find out the truth of ſuch pretended titles, before they can iuſtly make war, to diſpoſſeſſe any <hi>Prince</hi> of his proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right, by vertue of the <hi>Popes</hi> vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine authoritie to depriue <hi>Princes</hi> of their temporall Kingdomes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Wherfore this <hi>conſequence</hi> of yours is not good, although the <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> propoſition were ſuppoſed (as it is not) to be true.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:217:60"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Temporall Princes may make warre vpon probable titles, which are meerely temporall:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore the Pope and temporall Princes may make warre vpon probable titles, which are grounded chiefly vpon a probable ſpirituall authority.</hi> Becauſe there is no authoritie on earth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide <hi>infallibly</hi> the differences betwixt two abſolute Princes in <hi>meere</hi> tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affaires, wherein they are ſubiect to <hi>God</hi> alone, neither are there now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Prophets,</hi> as there were in the <hi>Ould Law,</hi> to declare vndoubtedly the truth, and will of <hi>God:</hi> And if there were now any ſuch infallible way, <hi>Princes</hi> were bound to try the ſame, before they could lawfully make war, onely vpon a probable title, againſt a <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath both a probable title and alſo poſſeſſion. But <hi>Christ</hi> hath left in his Church an vndoubted <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> way, to wit, the authoritie of an vndoubted <hi>Oecumenicall Councell,</hi> to determine and decide <hi>infallibly,</hi> what authoritie belongeth to the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> &amp; conſequently to determine <hi>infallibly</hi> all doubtfull and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:217:60"/>rights or titles depending thereon. Neither is it to the purpoſe, whether a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the <hi>Pope,</hi> be Superiour, and aboue the <hi>Pope</hi> or no; for neither doe I ſpeake here of a <hi>Generall Councell</hi> in this ſenſe, as it excludeth the <hi>Pope.</hi> but as it includeth all the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and doth perfectly repreſent the whole body of that <hi>Church,</hi> which is without all controuerſie <hi>the pillar and firmament of truth:</hi> and <hi>moreouer</hi> it is moſt certaine, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is no leſs ſubiect, and bound to ſubmit him ſelfe to the definitions of faith <hi>ex Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> to which <hi>Christ</hi> hath promiſed the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, then any inferiour Chriſtian whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And ſo likewiſe, if <hi>Christ</hi> had promiſed the like <hi>infallibilitie</hi> to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarie Iudges</hi> for the deciding of meere temporal cauſes, which he hath promiſed to a <hi>generall Councell</hi> for the deciding of ſpiritual, there is no doubt but that <hi>temporall Princes</hi> were bound to ſubmit themſelues to the iudgment of <hi>Arbitratours,</hi> before they could
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:217:61"/>lawfully make warre vpon any doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or controuerſed title, be it neuer ſo probable, againſt any <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath not only a probable title, but alſo poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>Finally,</hi> becauſe you ſtand ſo much vpon the lawfulneſs of making warre vpon a probable title againſt a <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath both a probable title and alſo poſſeſſion, conſider diligently (which the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>New-yeres gift</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">chap. 6 nu. 12.</note> recommended to Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes) whether if the French King (for example) or any other forrein Prince, ſhould vpon a meere temporall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable title to thoſe Dominions, which our <hi>Kings Maiestie</hi> poſſeſſeth, make warre againſt him, it be not manifeſt, that his <hi>Maiestie</hi> may lawfully, and all his ſubiects are bound to defend his <hi>Royall</hi> Perſon and Dominions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch inuaſions, and whether thoſe his <hi>Maiesties</hi> ſubiects, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curre with any forrein Prince to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade in that caſe his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and the Dominions which he poſſeſſeth, may lawfully be put to death, as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and conſequently, whether it
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:217:61"/>be not euident, that we may lawfully deteſt, abhorre, and abiure that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as manifeſtly falſe and indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or by a neceſſarie conſequence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to thoſe words of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> which houldeth, that they are not <hi>Traytours,</hi> nor can iuſtly be put to death, but rather doe well in taking part againſt their <hi>Soueraigne</hi> in the aforeſaid caſe. And neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, as I haue ſhewed aboue in the former <hi>Section,</hi> the falſhood and abſurditie of the Doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inuading of Princes, and ſeeking to diſpoſſeſſe them by warre, only by vertue of the <hi>Popes</hi> ſentence of depriuation, or vpon any probable title, which is grounded vpon a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſed Spirituall authoritie, is farre more manifeſt for the reaſon there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 14. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>LAstly,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> 
                     <hi>(ſay you)</hi> about this Branch your expoſition of thoſe words <hi>[as hereticall]</hi> ſeemeth to me
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:217:62"/>neither agreeing with the ordinarie, and common ſenſe of the words (which though ſomtimes may be taken in ſuch ſenſe as you expound them, yet ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily are not) nor with the intention of the Law-maker, who (thinking it to be against Scriptures, that the Pope ſhould haue power to depoſe Princes, for that none is aboue Kings (at the least in temporals) but God alone, and that by Scriptures) would haue all, no doubt, detest ſuch doctrine, as ſhall allow the depoſition of Princes, not only as hereticall, but for hereticall.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt it ſeemeth,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that you haue not well conſidered M. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> meaning and drift, in bringing this <hi>laſt</hi> anſwere, for the expounding of theſe words <hi>[as hereticall]</hi> in the <hi>fourth</hi> Branch of the Oath. For in his former anſwere he tooke the word <hi>[hereticall]</hi> for that, which is directly or indirectly repugnant to Scriptures, and in which ſence both <hi>Catholike Diuines</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and alſo <hi>Protestants,</hi> and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:217:62"/>his <hi>Maiestie</hi> do vnderſtand it; which ſenſe neuertheleſſe you aboue, in the third <hi>Section<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſeemed to diſproue in thoſe words <hi>[which ſenſe is not in my conceipt ſo proper neither with vs nor Protestants, who most of them hould that for heretical which ſubuerteth the foundation of faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and not that which is contrarie to Scripture]</hi> And yet now you will haue the Law-maker, who are <hi>Protestants,</hi> to take <hi>hereticall</hi> for that, which is againſt Scriptures. Now M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> taking <hi>hereticall</hi> in this ſenſe, to wit, for that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scriptures, either directly, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, and expreſly, or at the leaſt indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, vertually, and by a neceſſarie conſequence (which ſenſe I haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proued aboue to be proper and vſuall both among <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Catholikes</hi>) affirmed, that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine euen of <hi>depoſing Princes,</hi> being excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, may be abiured, not only <hi>as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall</hi> but <hi>for hereticall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. But becauſe ſome might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture contend (as you ſeeme to do) that the word <hi>[hereticall]</hi> according
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:217:63"/>to the common vnderſtanding of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, is to be taken onely for that, which is expreſſely declared by the Church to be <hi>hereticall,</hi> and repugnant to Scriptures, and which maketh a <hi>formall hereticke,</hi> and to be puniſhable, as an <hi>hereticke,</hi> by the Canons of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Lawes, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> in regard onely of ſuch contentious ſpirits, and admitting, for Diſputation ſake, that to bee true, which hee accounteth very falſe, gaue this laſt anſwer, to wit, that if wee will needs haue the word <hi>[hereticall]</hi> to bee taken for that doctrine, which is made <hi>hereticall</hi> by the Church, and maketh a <hi>formall heretike,</hi> and which before the declaration of the Church is not to be accounted <hi>hereticall,</hi> although it be a very falſe doctrine, and contrary to the word of God, then the Aduerb <hi>[as]</hi> doth ſignifie, both by vertue of the <hi>Word,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>matter,</hi> not an <hi>identity,</hi> or <hi>reality,</hi> but onely a <hi>ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</hi> of that ſtrict, and rigorous <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</hi> And this anſwer hee hath at large confirmed in his <hi>Adioynder</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzherberts</hi> Reply, where
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:217:63"/>you may ſee, that the Aduerbe <hi>[As]</hi> being an Aduerbe of ſimilitude, doth commonly, and not only ſometimes, or oftentimes, ſignifie onely a <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> by vertue of the <hi>Word,</hi> and that it neuer ſignifieth a <hi>reality, identity,</hi> or <hi>equality,</hi> but onely by reaſon of the <hi>matter,</hi> to which it is applyed. And that if the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>Branch</hi> will not permit, without manifeſt abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, that it ſignifie a <hi>realitie,</hi> wee are bound to interpret it in that ſenſe, which is not abſurd, according to the rules preſcribed by Diuines, for the interpreting of Lawes, vnleſſe either the words will not beare a true ſenſe, which as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath proued, is very falſe, or it bee apparant, that the intention of the <hi>Law-maker</hi> was to haue it taken in an <hi>abſurd,</hi> and <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient</hi> ſenſe, which were raſhneſſe and impiety, ſo to iudge of his <hi>Maieſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. For howſoeuer his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> be perſwaded in his opinion, iudgement, or beliefe, yet his intention is not, but that wee muſt take the words of the Oath, according to the common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of them, as it is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:217:64"/>euident by the <hi>Seuenth Branch.</hi> And therefore a great difference is to bee made betwixt his <hi>Maieſties</hi> beleefe, or perſwaſion, and his intention, as he is a Law-maker, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington,</hi> and the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>New-yeeres Gift</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">In the <hi>third</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</note> haue proued at large, by his <hi>Maieſties</hi> expreſſe declaration, who, although he be perſwaded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he is the <hi>ſupreme</hi> Lord of his Dominions, not onely in temporall, but alſo in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, for as much as concerneth the external gouernment by true coactiue authority, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not, by the inſtitution of <hi>Christ,</hi> any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to <hi>excommunicate</hi> him, yet his intention was not to meddle in this Oath with theſe poynts, nor to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh <hi>Catholikes</hi> from <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in points of Religion, but onely to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh <hi>Catholikes</hi> from <hi>Catholikes,</hi> in points of their loyalty and temporall allegeance; for in poynts of Religion, <hi>Catholikes</hi> were ſufficiently diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> by the Oath of Supremacie. Neither alſo is his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie</hi> perſwaded, that the doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> Princes depriued by the Pope
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:217:64"/>is <hi>hereticall,</hi> taking <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſtrict and rigorous ſenſe, for only that which is expreſſely and formally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Church, or ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted generall Councell, to be <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall:</hi> but he is perſwaded, that the ſayd doctrine is therefore <hi>hereticall,</hi> becauſe it is either directly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely, or indirectly and vertually, or by a neceſſary conſequence repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the holy Scriptures, in which ſenſe it may bee abiured not onely <hi>as hereticall,</hi> but alſo <hi>for hereticall,</hi> as hath beene ſhewed aboue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 15. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>THirdly,<note place="margin">Obiect.</note> I finde another difficultie <hi>(ſay you)</hi> about your doctrine of <hi>Declaratiue Breues.</hi> For you ſeeme to ſay, following therein the doctrine of <hi>Suarez,</hi> That <hi>Declaratiue Breues</hi> of Popes ſet forth, and publiſhed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſome thing, which the Church is in doubt of, do binde no further, then the Law, or ground, which they declare, and therefore if ſuch <hi>Breues</hi> bee but groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the <hi>Popes</hi> opinion (as theſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:217:65"/>ſeeme to you, which are ſet forth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the Oath is vulawfull) they binde no more then his opinion. Which doctrine of yours, and <hi>Suarez</hi> I muſt needs confeſſe, I cannot well conceiue, or vnderſtand. For to me it ſeemeth, that <hi>Breues</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>declaratiue,</hi> or <hi>definitiue,</hi> for the certainty of their obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould not depend on the ground, or Law, which they declare, or define, but on the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, promiſed to the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> when they ſhall declare, or define any thing <hi>ex Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> for the whole Church to be lawfull, or vnlawfull (which declaration is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and in effect a definition) in my conceit that declaration muſt binde for the aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the ground therof bee a formall Law, or but onely an opinion: and ſo if the <hi>Pope</hi> haue the infallible aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt in his definitions and declarations <hi>ex Cathedra</hi> (as in <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> opinion he hath, though in yours not, and that alſo probably) and intended in his <hi>Breues</hi> to declare to the whole Church <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> that the Oath is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:217:65"/>vnlawfull, I ſee not why it ſhould not ſo bee thought and taken, whether the ground of ſuch declaration was his only opinion, or no. And ſo wee ſee, that if the whole Church ſhould in a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> declare any thing to bee lawfull, or vnlawfull, which before was in doubt (as is now of this Oath) when wee all agree, that ſhe hath the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt in her generall decrees, as well as in her definitions, wee ought to to take it for ſuch, whether the ground of her declaration be certaine, or onely but probable. The ſame (I would think) ſhould bee thought of the declaratiue <hi>Breues</hi> of <hi>Popes,</hi> at the leaſt in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of thoſe, who maintaine, that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot erre no more without a <hi>Councell,</hi> then with it: For if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of any ſuch thing to be lawfull, or vnlawfull ſhould binde vs no more, then the ground of that declaration, whether it were a formall Law, or but onely an opinion, ſuch declaration were but idle, and ſhould not afford that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie and ſatisfaction, which at the Church is required in time of doubt. I know you anſwer this difficulty about
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:217:66"/>the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> ſufficiently, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the <hi>Pope</hi> may erre in decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or defining without a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> and that there was no ſuch <hi>Councell,</hi> when theſe <hi>Breues</hi> were ſet forth; but this difficultie I finde about your doctrine, and much more about the doctrine of <hi>Suarez,</hi> of <hi>Declaratiue Breues,</hi> becauſe you ſtand not vpon that anſwer onely.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVt <hi>firſt,</hi> it is manifeſt in my iudgement, that in all <hi>declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue precepts,</hi> eſpecially belonging to manners, or of things to bee done, or omitted (for onely of theſe precepts, &amp; not of definitions, declarations, or precepts of faith, or of things to bee beleeued, <hi>Suarez</hi> ſpeaketh) the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the precept dependeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fundamentall ground, reaſon, &amp; end of the precept: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo is implyed the intention and will of the <hi>Law-maker</hi> (which is the <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of the Law) who inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth onely to binde by his <hi>declaratiue
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:217:66"/>precept,</hi> for as much onely as the thing he commandeth, or forbiddeth, is of it owne nature neceſſarie, or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to ſome former Law of <hi>God, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or ſome other <hi>poſitiue Law,</hi> which the declaratiue precept doth declare and ſuppoſe: And therefore (as <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> well obſerueth) a <hi>pure declaratiue precept</hi> doth not make the thing, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it forbiddeth, to be vnlawfull, but only ſuppoſeth and declareth it to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, as forbidden by ſome former Law. Whereupon it followeth, that if it bee but a probable opinion, that there is ſuch a former Law, the <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue precept</hi> can binde no more, then the probabilitie of the opinion (which is the fundamentall ground and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the precept) hath force to bind.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Neither doth your obiection impugne this manifeſt doctrine. For, although in ſuch generall precepts, wherein the <hi>Church</hi> cannot erre, to wit, when ſhee commadeth the <hi>whole Church</hi> ſomething, which is neceſſary to ſaluation, the certainty and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the precept dependeth vpon the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, yet
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:217:67"/>this doth not hinder, but that it muſt alſo depend vpon the ſubſtantiall ground, reaſon, and end, for which the Law was made. But this onely at the moſt is proued by your obiection, that becauſe the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt is annexed to the precept, it muſt conſequently bee annexed to all thoſe things, whereon the precept doth neceſſarily depend: But to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme therefore, that the precept doth depend on nothing elſe, then vpon the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, were ridiculous.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As alſo due diligence and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the cauſe is, according to the doctrine of all Diuines, neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required in a <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine infallibly any doctrine of faith: And becauſe the aſſiſtance of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is annexed to her definition, it muſt conſequently be alſo annexed to all that, whereon her infallible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition doth neceſſarily depend. And thereupon the Diuines affirme, that if it be certaine, that the Church did not erre in her definition, it is alſo certain, that ſhe vſed due diligence, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:217:67"/>neceſſary conditions, which by the inſtitution of Chriſt are required to an infallible definition: But to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that becauſe the infallibilitie of her definition dependeth vpon the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, therefore neither due diligence, nor examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cauſe, nor any other thing is neceſſarily required to her infallible definition, were abſurd &amp; ridiculous.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Wherefore you muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt <hi>fundamentall, intrinſecall,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> reaſons, or grounds, and <hi>Extrinſecall,</hi> or <hi>accidental,</hi> as M. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath often affirmed from the doctrine of <hi>Bellarm:</hi> &amp; <hi>Canus,</hi> to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> alſo all other Diuines doe agree: for theſe laſt may be falſe, and yet the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition true. As in the ſecond <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of <hi>Nice</hi> it was declared, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels might bee painted, becauſe they haue bodies, the declaration was true, although this reaſon, being <hi>extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> and <hi>accidentall,</hi> was falſe. But if ſhee had declared, that it is lawfull to paint Angels, becauſe it is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to faith, or good manners, which is a <hi>fundamentall</hi> ground, and reaſon
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:217:68"/>of that declaration, the declaration can not be true, if that <hi>fundamentall</hi> reaſon and ground be ſuppoſed to be falſe. And thus much concerning the doctrine of <hi>Suarez</hi> in generall.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 And therefore <hi>ſecondly,</hi> to apply it to the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> if it were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the <hi>Pope,</hi> in making his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue prohibition of the Oath, had the infallible aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> would not ſticke to affirme, that as the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is infallible, ſo conſequenly the <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall</hi> reaſon and ground, for which the Oath is by the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> forbidden, is alſo infallible: and that therefore ſome thing is in the Oath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to faith or ſaluation, which is the <hi>fundamentall</hi> ground, reaſon, and end of the <hi>Popes</hi> forbidding the Oath: for if there were nothing in the Oath againſt faith or ſaluation, the <hi>Pope</hi> could not forbid it with ſuch iniurie to his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and ſo great damage to Engliſh Catholikes.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 But <hi>thirdly,</hi> this obiection of yours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> concerning the infallible aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the holy Ghoſt, promiſed to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:217:68"/>the <hi>Church</hi> for the making of general precepts <hi>ex Cathedra</hi> either touching faith or manners, doth not ſufficiently confirme the infallibilitie of the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> forbidding Engliſh Catholikes to take the Oath: for that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">in his <hi>Theologicall Diſputation</hi> cap. 10. ſect. 2.</note> hath clearely proued, that the <hi>Pope</hi> both might erre in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Breues,</hi> not onely becauſe they were made without a <hi>generall Councell</hi> (which neuertheleſſe, as you very well grant, were ſufficient to proue, that he might erre therein) but alſo becauſe they are not <hi>generall precepts,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the whole Church, but containe only a <hi>particular</hi> precept di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to one particular nation (and therefore they are well called by <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daemon Ioannes</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">
                        <hi>in</hi> Praefat. paraleli tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> the <hi>Popes priuate let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to Engliſh Catholikes admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them not to take the Oath) wherin not onely the <hi>Pope</hi> but alſo a <hi>generall Councell</hi> may erre (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdrington</hi> obſerueth out of the doctrine of <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Canus</hi>);<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bell.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Rom. Pont. ca. <hi>2. Canus</hi> lib. <hi>1 5.</hi> de locis c. <hi>5.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> And alſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> did erre in thoſe <hi>Breues</hi> vpon falſe informations and ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to wit, for that he ſuppoſed his
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:217:69"/>Primacie in ſpirituals, his power to bind and loſe, to excommunicate and inflict Cenſures to bee denyed in the Oath, which is manifeſtly falſe, &amp; that his power to depoſe Princes is moſt certaine and of faith, and not queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among Catholikes, which is no leſſe vntrue, is ſufficiently conuinced by him in his <hi>Theological Diſputation</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">in the place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and in his anſwere to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fitzher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                        <hi>part.</hi> 3.6.17.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>Sect. 16. Obiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>A</hi> Fourth difficultie I find <hi>(ſay you)</hi> about the ſwearing, <hi>that this Oath is miniſtred vnto me by lawfull authoritie:</hi> Whereupon it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, we may vſe no equiuocation in taking of the ſame, for that none can equiuocate in an Oath, that is exacted by lawfull authoritie: For if it were certaine, that no thing is exacted by this Oath, but temporall allegiance, then wee might not onely ſweare, but were alſo bound to ſweare, that ſuch Oath were ministred by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: But when it is questionable
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:217:69"/>and vncertain, whether the Pope hath power to depoſe Princes or no, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, whether the Prince exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſuch an Oath of his Subiects, ſhould cauſe them wrong the Pope and Church, and make them ſweare a thing vncertaine, and with the hurt of their conſciences, not being able ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them to conforme themſelues to thoſe conceipts you frame of the Oath, though they were true, for that they can perceiue no ſolid ground therfore, I ſee not how we may ſweare, that this Oath is ministred vnto vs by lawfull authoritie.</q>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 BVt <hi>first</hi> it is not true, that we muſt <hi>ſweare,</hi> that this Oath is miniſtred vnto vs by lawfull authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but only that we muſt <hi>acknowledge</hi> ſo much, of which our acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is the immediate obiect of the Oath, we muſt be aſſured to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs from periurie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is very true, that we muſt not equiuocate in this Oath; and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:217:70"/>this is not only deduced from the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miniſtring of the ſame (although this bee ſufficient to proue, that wee muſt not equiuocate therein) but it is alſo deduced from the <hi>Seuenth branch</hi> wherein it is expreſly ordained, that me muſt vſe no equiuocation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the lawfulnes, or vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Branch dependeth wholy vpon the former Clauſes: for if none of the former Clauſes containe a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of any ſpirituall obedience due to the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> nor be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to truth, or iuſtice, it is manifeſt, that they are miniſtred by lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. And therefore you muſt <hi>firſt</hi> proue, that ſome one of the former clauſes is repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to truth or iuſtice, before you can impugne the Oath as not miniſtred by lawfull authoritie. Whereupon you return backe to that which you aboue obiected againſt the <hi>ſecond Branch,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depoſe Princes, <hi>which</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is vncertaine and questionable &amp;c.</hi> But, as I anſwered there, it is certain to me (neither can any man of learning that wel examineth the queſtion, otherwiſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:217:70"/>in my iudgement conceiue) that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no true, reall, lawfull power and authoritie, and which may be a ſufficient ground to depoſe Princes, or to practiſe their depoſition, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an imaginarie power, in the conceit onely and approbation of ſome men, which neuertheleſſe is no true, reall, lawfull and ſufficient power to puniſh any Prince by depriuing him of the Dominions which he poſſeſſeth. And conſequently the <hi>Kings Maiestie</hi> in cauſing his ſubiects to acknowledge and ſwear, that the Pope hath no true, reall, lawful authority, and which may be a ſufficient ground to depoſe him (thereby to be the better ſecured from all inuaſions vnder pretence of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to diſcouer his loyall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſubiects from thoſe who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the principles of the <hi>Powder-Traytours</hi>) doth neither wrong the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor <hi>Church,</hi> nor cauſe his ſubiects to wrong them, or their conſciences, but ſeeketh to preſerue his owne right and Dominions which he really poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth, from all inuaſions and <hi>Powder-Treaſons,</hi> vnder colour of any proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:217:71"/>or imaginary power or title, which is grounded vpon an vncertaine and controuerſed ſpirituall authority. But contrariwiſe the <hi>Pope</hi> in forbidding this Oath, which cannot ſufficiently be proued to be vnlawfull, doth wrong <hi>himſelfe,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> and this whole kingdome: And thoſe Engliſh Catholikes, that bend their wits to find out ſcruples, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauills againſt the Oath, and to wreſt the words to the worſt ſenſe that may be, whereas they may expound them in a fauourable ſenſe, doe wrong the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> his <hi>Maieſtie, themſelues,</hi> and all their <hi>Catholike brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>But many</hi> (ſay you) <hi>are not able to conforme themſelues to thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipts</hi> Widdrington <hi>frameth of the Oath, though they were true, for that they cannot perceiue any ſolid ground there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But <hi>Firſt,</hi> if they be learned, they may eaſily conforme themſelues to <hi>Widdringtons</hi> explication of the Oath, if they will diligently, and without partialitie examine the ſoliditie of his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:217:71"/>proofes, and couſider, that his proofes and anſweres are grounded, not only vpon his own conceipt, but vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt reaſon, his <hi>Maieſties</hi> declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the doctrine and authoritie of moſt learned Diuines, and which is more, euen of thoſe, who be his <hi>chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Aduerſaries</hi> in this point: and if withall they will remember (as M. <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath heretofore<note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>In the</hi> Epiſtle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatorie <hi>of his</hi> Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued) that no other ſolid ground, or proofe is ſufficient to confute the Oath, but euident demonſtrations, but to proue the Oath to be lawfull, and that it may be lawfully taken, it is a very ſufficient and ſolid ground, to anſwer probably to all the arguments, which are brought againſt the ſame: which whether he hath performed, or no, and what kinde of demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or rather moſt weake arguments, the impugners of the Oath haue brought, (ſeeing that few of them can ſcarſe agree in any one conceipt) I dare remit euen to your owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Secondly,</hi> if they be altogither ſo vnlearned, that neither by their
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:217:72"/>owne reading, nor naturall iudgment, they are able to examine the ſoliditie of the grounds of this controuerſie, they muſt be guided, inſtructed, and directed by the learned, who if through ignorance, negligence, want of due examination, inconſiderate zeale, or partialitie either towards <hi>Popes,</hi> or <hi>Princes,</hi> they direct them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, the chiefeſt fault is in the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors,</hi> and <hi>Inſtructors,</hi> for which they are greatly to anſwer at the day of iudgement: and how farre theſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, being guided and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted amiſſe, are to be excuſed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and before the ſight of God, I will not iudge, but leaue it to his iudgement, who is the ſearcher of all mens hearts. This onely I wiſh them to remember, that temporall <hi>Princes</hi> doe not in their Tribunalls meddle with their conſciences, but onely with their externall actions, for which they may ſometimes be iuſtly puniſhed by the externall Magiſtrate, although their conſcience be neuer ſo cleare in the ſight of God.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if ſome either can not,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:217:72"/>or can, but will not conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to <hi>Wiiddringtons</hi> conceipts and explication of the Oath, to which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe others both can, and doe conforme themſelues, will you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inferre from hence, that the Oath <hi>is of it ſelfe</hi> vnlawfull, or not <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred to them by lawfull authoritie?</hi> Call to mind, how aboue in your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the <hi>ſecond Branch</hi> you affirmed without any proofe at all, that to deny the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depoſe, is not to deny the power and authoritie it ſelfe; and yet now from the deniall of the <hi>practiſe</hi> of the lawful authoritie to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Oath to ſome, who can not conforme themſelues to <hi>Widdringtons</hi> conceipts, and explication of the Oath, you would inferre, alſo without any proofe, a deniall of the authority it ſelfe to miniſter lawfully the Oath to them. But the plaine truth is, as I obſerued there, that a deniall of all ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and practiſes of any power or authoritie is a vertuall deniall of the power and authoritie it ſelfe, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of ſome particular effects &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:217:73"/>is not a ſufficient, or vertuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of the authoritie it ſelfe. And therefore although we ſhould grant, as we doe not, that the State can not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, or without ſinne, miniſter this Oath to thoſe who cannot conforme themſelues to <hi>Widdringtons</hi> conceipts and explication of the Oath, to which neuertheleſſe other Catholickes both can, and doe conforme themſelues, yet it can not be inferred from hence, that the Oath is not miniſtred to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by lawfull authority. As alſo although we ſhould admit, as we doe not, that a Iudge cannot lawfully, or without ſinne, miniſter an Oath to him, whom he morally knoweth wil ſweare falſly, and againſt his conſcience, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be inferred from hence, that the Iudge hath not good and full power and authoritie to miniſter the Oath to him. For one may haue authoritie to a thing, which neuertheleſſe in ſome caſes he cannot lawfully doe. As a Prieſt being in mortall ſinne hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to miniſter the Sacraments, (for example of Penance) and yet as a Prieſt he cannot lawfully miniſter
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:217:73"/>them being in mortall ſinne: and therefore although he commit ſinne by vſing and exerciſing his Office ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religiouſly, yet the Sacrament is valid becauſe his being in ſinne doth not depriue him of his authority, neither doth he ſinne in that manner, as he ſhould doe, who miniſtreth the ſaid Sacrament without prieſtly authority. See <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his Anſwere to Maſter Fitzherb. part. 2. chap. 10. nu. 33. pag. 286. et ſeq. where he hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth this matter more at large.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> according to your manner of arguing, you might alſo proue, that the <hi>King</hi> hath not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to miniſter an Oath to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, that they ſhall acknowledge his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> to be their <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> in temporals; and yet Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe affirmeth,<note place="margin">In the iudgment <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 13 16.</note> that <hi>there is no Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like who ſticketh, or maketh difficultie to acknowledge and ſweare the ſame.</hi> And <hi>Becanus</hi> alſo in the firſt Edition of his <hi>Controuerſia Anglicana</hi> pag. 101. affirmeth, <hi>that it is certaine to him, that King</hi> Iames <hi>is the Soueraigne Lord in temporalls ouer his Dominions.</hi> For to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:217:74"/>vſe the like argument you framed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue; If it were certaine, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is exacted by the aforeſaid Oath but temporall Allegiance, then we might not onely ſweare, but alſo were bound to ſweare, that ſuch an Oath were miniſtred by lawfull authoritie. But when it is queſtionable and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, whether the <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> or the <hi>Popes Holineſſe</hi> be the <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> in temporalls, not onely of this Kingdome, but (according to the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts</hi> doctrine, which moſt learned <hi>Victoria</hi> affirmeth to be <hi>altogither im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable,</hi> as in very deede it is) of all the Chriſtian Kingdoms in the world, and conſequently whether the <hi>King</hi> exacting ſuch an Oath of his Subiects ſhould cauſe them wrong the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> or make them ſweare a thing vncertaine, or with the hurt of their conſciences, not being able many of them to conform themſelues to thoſe conceipts, which the <hi>Diuines,</hi> who are oppoſite therein to the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> doe make of ſuch an Oath, though they were true, for that they can perceiue no ſolid ground therefore, I ſee not,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:217:74"/>how we may lawfully ſweare, that ſuch an Oath is miniſtred vnto vs by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full authoritie. But how inſufficient this manner of arguing is, I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed partly in this Section, and partly aboue in the Second.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Fiftly, if we follow M. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dringtons</hi> firſt anſwer, which you can not convince to be improbable, to wit, that the immediate Obiect of this Oath, is onely our ſincere acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement and perſwaſion, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any lawfull power or authoritie to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> and not the abſolute propoſition, then the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument you make here is of no force at all, for of this our acknowledgment we muſt be and are moſt certaine and aſſured. And neuertheleſſe you know right well, that to proue any Branch of the Oath vnlawfull, you muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne all the explications M. <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath made of that Branch, &amp; that not onely with probable excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but with euident and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing demonſtrations.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:217:75"/>
               <head>Sect. 17. Obiection.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>LAst,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> I doe not ſee <hi>(ſay you)</hi> how and one, that is not altogither of your opinions in all theſe points belonging to the Oath, can ſweare, that he doth it willingly, for that none doth willingly ſweare againſt his owne opinions, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he might perhaps doe it, if the opinion be probable, vnleſſe we take <hi>[willingly]</hi> for <hi>voluntarium ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid,</hi> which willingneſſe is neither proper, nor ſufficient, as your ſelfe will grant.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your old acquaintance, if he be not deceiued, M. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BVt <hi>first,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Anſ.</note> this exception of yours doth not proue the Oath to be <hi>of it ſelfe</hi> vnlawfull, but at the moſt, that ſome, who are not of <hi>Widdringtens</hi> opinion in ad theſe points, can not
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:217:75"/>take it againſt their opinion, or rather againſt their conſcience: And the ſame exception you might make, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Oath ſhould ouely containe, that <hi>King Iames</hi> is our <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> in temporalls. But this exception doth not proue, that thoſe, who be of <hi>Widdringtons</hi> opinion in all theſe points, belonging to the Oath, may not ſweare, that they take it <hi>willingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> albeit ſome be of this opinion, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath authority to depoſe Princes, yet vnleſſe they hold it for certaine, and a poynt of faith, and the contrarie doctrine alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th crimprobable, and out of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among Catholikes, which neuertheleſſe all the world ſeeth to be a great controuerſie among them, they may, notwithſtanding their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, take the Oath lawfully and <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,</hi> for that they may, and ought perſwade their conſciences aſſuredly, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any true, reall, ſufficient, or lawfull power to depoſe Princes, or to practiſe their depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the true and plaine mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Second</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> Branch.</p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:217:76"/>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> whereas you ſeeme to inſinuate, that thoſe things, which are done through feare, are onely <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria ſecundum quid, willing in ſome ſort,</hi> but not <hi>ſimply,</hi> and <hi>properly willing,</hi> and ſo he, that ſhould for feare of looſing his libertie and goods, and incurring his <hi>Maieſties</hi> diſpleaſure, take this Oath againſt his owne opinion, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo conſcience, ſhould not take it <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, ſimpliciter</hi> &amp; <hi>proprie, ſimply</hi> and <hi>properly,</hi> but onely <hi>ſecundum quid, in ſome ſort,</hi> you are herein greatly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken. For, according to the common doctrine of all Philoſophers and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, feare doth onely cauſe <hi>involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarium ſecundum quid, vnwillingneſſe in ſome ſort;</hi> and thoſe things, which are done through feare, are <hi>ſimply willing,</hi> which <hi>willingneſſe</hi> is both proper and ſufficient: Doe not many both ſweare and forſweare very <hi>willingly,</hi> againſt their opinions, yea, and conſciences alſo, for loue of their ſenſuall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, for hope of great gaine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, for feare of great danger, for procuring the fauour of <hi>Princes,</hi> and auoyding of their indignation? You
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:217:76"/>know, that a great loue and concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of any thing, which we greatly deſire, doth not cauſe <hi>vnwillingneſſe,</hi> but rather increaſe it, and that where there is a great loue and deſire of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any thing, there is alſo a great feare of looſing, or not obtaining it. A Marchant doth very <hi>willingly, hic et nunc,</hi> in this particular caſe, when he is in danger of drowning, caſt his goods into the Sea to ſaue his life, which hee more loueth and reſpecteth, then his goods. And many men, who preferre their corporall pleaſures, and the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of corporall puniſhment, before their ſoules health, doe very <hi>willingly hic et nunc,</hi> in this particular caſe, ſpeak, and doe many things againſt their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and conſciences alſo. But it ſeemeth, that you abſtract from <hi>hic et nunc,</hi> from <hi>this particular caſe,</hi> and that you conſider <hi>voluntarium,</hi> or <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> if that particular caſe were not, which is the cauſe of your errour, or miſtaking, for <hi>quae fiunt ex metu, ſunt hic &amp; nunc ſimpliciter, abſolutè, efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; propriè voluntaria, thoſe things that are done for feare, are, hic &amp; nunc,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:217:77"/>in this particular caſe ſimply, abſolutely, actually, effectually,</hi> and <hi>properly done willingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> ſuppoſing the Oath to be lawfull, and miniſtred by lawfull authoritie, an other moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>willingneſſe</hi> is to be found in tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Oath, as likewiſe in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of all iuſt lawes. For we are bound to obſerue all iuſt lawes both of <hi>God,</hi> (although eternall damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſoule and bodie be threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the breakers of the ſame) and alſo of <hi>man,</hi> (although great tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhments are impoſed vpon the tranſgreſſours thereof) not for feare of puniſhment, but <hi>heartily, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,</hi> and <hi>ſincerely,</hi> for the loue of vertue, and for the duty and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we owe to <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King:</hi> as it hath beene inſinuated in the <hi>New-yeeres-gift,</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</note> and declared more at large by M. <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologicall Diſputation.</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> And therefore vnleſſe you can ſufficiently proue ſome one of the former branches to be vnlawfull, you neede not inſiſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this clauſe, which according to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:217:77"/>your grounds, is therefore vnlawfull, becauſe ſome one of the former clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is vnlawfull: albeit, as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you cannot ſufficiently proue that this Oath may not, <hi>hic et nunc,</hi> ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the great temporall harme is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred by refuſing it, be taken <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> by ſome, who prefer their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtate and goods of body and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune before their ſoules health, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we ſhould falſly ſuppoſe the Oath to be vnlawfull: &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this clauſe may be true in regard of ſome that take it <hi>willingly,</hi> although they ſhould ſuppoſe ſome one, or all of the former clauſes to be repugnant to truth or iuſtice.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And thus you ſee <hi>(good Sir)</hi> that I haue taken a little paines, and ſpent ſome time, which in very deede I could hardly at this preſent haue ſpared, to anſwer all your difficulties in particular, partly for your owne ſake and ſatisfaction, and partly of others, who, as I ſuppoſe, haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred with you herein, whom, as alſo your ſelfe both in regard of our anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent acquaintance, and your ſingular
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:217:78"/>learning and great zeale, I much loue and reſpect. And truely I make no doubt, but that if you had beene as diligent to finde out arguments and anſwers in fauour of the Oath, as you haue beene to invent <hi>ſcruples</hi> againſt the ſame, you would quickly haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that no one Clauſe of the Oath can be ſufficiently proued to be vnlawfull: eſpecially if you had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, that to proue the Oath to be vnlawfull, euident demonſtrations are required, but to proue it lawfull, only probable arguments and anſweres are ſufficient; and alſo that I haue here ſaid nothing, but what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath either expreſſely ſaid before, or may be clearely deduced from the grounds of his doctrine. And ſo wiſhing you all happineſſe, I take my leaue, hoping, that if, notwithſtanding this my anſwer, you cannot conforme your conſcience to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Widdringtons</hi> conceipts &amp; explication of the Oath, yet you will not condemne thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, who both can and doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelues therevnto; and that you will not be any cauſe, or occaſion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:217:78"/>in word or deede, of making a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, diſvnion, or Schiſme among your Catholike brethren by exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them vniuſtly from Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Sacraments in regard of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, for which in <hi>France</hi> they are not excluded, nor thought vnworthy to be admitted therevnto, and which (as <hi>Card. Peron</hi> notably obſerueth) <hi>ought not to hinder the revnion of thoſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Peron</hi> in his laſt great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>cap.</hi> 91. <hi>pag</hi> 633.</note> 
                     <hi>who</hi> are out of the Church, &amp; ſhould <hi>deſire to be reconciled therevnto,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſeing that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary doctrin hath bin in <hi>France</hi> by many publike <hi>Edicts</hi> of <hi>Roman. Catholikes,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned vnder paine of <hi>high treaſon,</hi> for <hi>falſe, pernitious, ſcandalous,</hi> and <hi>ſeditious;</hi> but that you will ſeeke, as you wiſhed aboue, to make an happy atonement, reconcilement, and peace among them, and not ouer raſhly and vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably to cenſure, for any point which is controuerſie among Catholikes, their conſciences, who, for cleare and vndoubted points of Catholike Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are as ready and willing to looſe by patient ſuffering, their goods, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:217:79"/>and life it ſelfe, as your ſelfe, or any other Catholike whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>London</hi> 
                        <date>this 13. of Nouemb. 1620.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your very louing friend, and ancient Schoolefellow, <hi>R. P.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In the <hi>Summarie</hi> pag. C 2. lin. 5. read <hi>hath not.</hi> pag. 14. after the words <hi>King</hi> &amp;c. adde, <hi>but onely our ſincere acknowledgment thereof.</hi> pag. 93. lin. 24. <hi>commandeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:217:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
